<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<pollutants>
  <pollutant id="1">
    <pollutant_name>Methane (CH4)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Methane is a major constituent of natural gas and is burned to heat buildings. Also, it can be used as a fuel for power stations to produce electricity, and used in the production of more complex chemicals.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Methane is both naturally occurring and man made. The major naturally occurring source is from the decomposition of plant and animal matter. The major human activity sources include waste disposal, agriculture and coal mining.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>	Natural levels of methane in the environment are not detrimental to health. </text>
	<text>Methane is an important greenhouse gas emitted both naturally and as a as a result of human activities. Human activities have resulted in methane concentrations in the atmosphere to increase by over 100% compared to the pre-industrial era. Although in absolute terms less methane than CO2 is emitted into the environment, its global warming potential is 25 times that of carbon dioxide over a 100 year time horizon according to the IPCC 4th assessment report. As a volatile organic compound (VOC) at the global scale methane also contributes to the formation of harmful ground level ozone which can cause damage to human health and plants.
Methane gas build-up from landfill sites is a potential explosion hazard.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Gas</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-182.6</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>-161.4</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>466000</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>24.2</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>1.09</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>5% - 15%</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>-188</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>537</autoignition_temp>
    <density>0.0007168</density>
    <vapour_density>0.55</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>Essentially non-toxic; asphyxiant</toxicity>
    <persistence>Not persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>No adverse effects expected</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>No adverse effects expected</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Methane is a colourless gas and odourless at low concentrations, although has a sweetish chloroform-like odour when in high concentrations.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="1">
        <standard>EN 13526:2001</standard>
        <title>Determination of the mass concentration of total gaseous organic carbon in flue gases from solvent using processes. Continuous flame ionisation detector method.  (NOTE:This method is not specific to CH4)</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, at a 95% level of confidence, ranges between  +/-0.8mg/m<sup>3</sup> for values about 10 mg/m<sup>3</sup> and +/-29 mg/m<sup>3</sup> at values about 200 mg/m<sup>3</sup> </uncertainty>
      </provision>
	  <provision id="1">
        <standard>EN 12619:1999</standard>
        <title>Determination of the mass concentration of total gaseous organic carbon at low concentrations in flue gases - Continuous flame ionisation detector method. (NOTE:This method is not specific to CH4)</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, at a 95% level of confidence, ranges between  +/-0.3 mg/m<sup>3</sup> for values about 1 mg/m<sup>3</sup> and +/-0.4 mg/m<sup>3</sup> at values about 10 to 15 mg/m<sup>3</sup></uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="2">
    <pollutant_name>Carbon monoxide (CO)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Carbon monoxide is both man-made and produced naturally. The major use of carbon dioxide is in the metal refining and chemical industry.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Most releases originate from vehicles that are not fitted with a catalytic converter. Levels of carbon monoxide are also believed to reflect traffic volumes in urban areas. Natural processes only produce small amounts in comparison.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Long-term exposure at a low concentrations can result in neurological problems and harm to unborn babies. </text>
	<text>Carbon monoxide can react with other pollutants to produce ground level ozone, an important pollutant at local and global scales. Elevated levels of ozone can cause respiratory health problems and can lead to premature mortality. High levels of O3 also damage plants, reducing agricultural crop yields and decreasing forest growth.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Gas</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-205</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>-191</boiling_point>
    <water_solubility>2.3</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>3.17</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>12.5% - 74%</flammable_limits>
    <autoignition_temp>620</autoignition_temp>
    <vapour_density>0.97</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>LC 50 (1 H) 3760 ppm / 1807 ppm, 4h</toxicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Lepomis Humilis - 37500 ug/l - 1 d</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Carbon monoxide is a colourless, odourless poisonous gas.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="2">
        <standard>EN 15058:2006</standard>
        <title>Reference method for the determination of carbon monoxide in emission by means of the non-dispersive infrared method</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions </target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, at a 95% level of confidence, is +/- 2.8 mg/m<sup>3</sup> for values at about 50 mg/m<sup>3</sup></uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="2">
        <standard>ISO 12039:2001</standard>
        <title>Determination of carbon monoxide, carbon dioxide and oxygen - Performance characteristics and calibration of automated measuring systems</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions </target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, at a 95% level of confidence, is less than 10% of full scale. </uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="3">
    <pollutant_name>Carbon Dioxide (CO2)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Carbon dioxide has many uses. Its main uses are as coolant, fire extinguishant, preservative, fizz in  drinks and to produce smoke effects.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
      <text>Carbon dioxide occurs mainly from natural processes, notably respiration by living organisms. Releases from respiration are balanced by similar quantities absorbed by plants during the photosynthesis. Smaller quantities are released by volcanoes, fires and evaporation from seawater.</text>
      <text>The release of carbon dioxide from man made activities originates from the combustion of fuel containing carbon such as coal, oil and natural gas for industrial, domestic and transport purposes.</text>
    </main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
      <text>Natural levels of CO<sub>2</sub> in the environment are not detrimental to health.</text>
      <text>The main environmental concern with respect to carbon dioxide is the significant role this compound plays as a greenhouse gas influencing climate change. Together with certain other greenhouse gases, emissions of CO<sub>2</sub> are controlled in a number of developed countries through the UNFCCC’s Kyoto protocol.</text>
    </health_affects>
    <state>Gas</state>
    <boiling_point>-78.5, Sublimes</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>760</vapour_pressure>
    <partition_coeff>0.83</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>Non flammable</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>700</autoignition_temp>
    <density>0.0001976</density>
    <vapour_density>1.53</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>470000</toxicity>
    <persistence>Not persistent</persistence>
    <description>Carbon dioxide is a colourless, odourless gas naturally present in the atmosphere. It is slightly soluble in water, forming carbonic acid.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="3">
        <standard>ISO 12039:2001</standard>
        <title>Determination of carbon monoxide, carbon dioxide and oxygen - Performance characteristics and calibration of automated measuring systems</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions </target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, at a 95% level of confidence, is less than 10% of full scale.</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="4">
    <pollutant_name>Hydro-fluorocarbons (HFCs)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>The major use of HFCs is as a refrigerant in refrigeration and air-conditioning equipment. They are also used as a propellant in industrial aerosols as well as for foam blowing, solvent cleaning and in fire extinguishers. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Major releases are from refrigeration equipment both during operation and end of life destruction.</text>
	<text>Minor releases arise from their use in aerosols.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>HFCs at concentrations typically found in the environment will have no impact on health and the local environment. </text>
	<text>The main environmental concern with HFCs is the role these compounds play as greenhouse gases influencing climate change. Their global warming potential can be around 100-15,000 times higher than carbon dioxide over a 100 year time horizon according to the IPCC 4th assessment report; however their use is generally limited to specific industrial applications. HFCs are stable pollutants; they can persist in the environment for up to hundreds of years.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Gas</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-160</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>-84.4</boiling_point>
    <water_solubility>733</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>0.64</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>Non flammable</flash_point>
    <toxicity>Practically non-toxic</toxicity>
    <description>Hydro-fluorocarbons (HFCs) are a group of chemicals containing hydrogen, fluorine and carbon atoms. They are generally colourless and odourless gases which are chemically unreactive.  Trifluoromethane, a hydro-fluorocarbon, is provided as an example. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
	  <provision id="4">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title>The 2006 IPCC Guidelines for National Greenhouse Gas Inventories provide information on estimating emissions (Volume 3)</title>
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
	</iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="5">
    <pollutant_name>Nitrous Oxide (N2O)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Nitrous oxide is an oxidiser that has a variety of uses. In industrial processes to manufacture nylon and nitric acid, as an anaesthetic (commonly known as laughing gas) and as an oxidiser in motor sport and rocketry to increase the power of engines.  </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Nitrous oxide is produced by natural and man-made sources. The main releases are from the natural microbial processes of nitrification and de-nitrification, however these natural processes are increased by the application of nitrogen fertilizers and animal manures to crops and pastures. Nitrous oxide is also released during the combustion of fossil fuels and from industrial processes.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Long term exposure to low levels of nitrous oxide may have effects on the bone marrow and peripheral nervous system. It may also cause reproductive toxicity.  </text>
	<text>Nitrous oxide is one of the main greenhouse gases considered in the UNFCCC’s Kyoto protocol together with carbon dioxide and methane. Although its emissions to the environment are smaller, the global warming potential of nitrous oxide over a 100 year time horizon is around 300 times greater than that of carbon dioxide. Nitrous oxide is also important as an ozone depleting substance.  </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Gas</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-90.8</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>-88.5</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>42900</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>2.2</water_solubility>
    <vapour_density>1.53</vapour_density>
    <description>Nitrous oxide is a non-flammable, colourless gas with a pleasant, slightly sweet odour.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="5">
        <standard>ISO 10396:2007</standard>
        <title>Sampling for the automated determination of gas emission concentrations for permanently-installed monitoring systems</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>-</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="6">
    <pollutant_name>Ammonia (NH3)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Ammonia is both manufactured and produced naturally. It is used for bleaching and cleaning, for fertilisers and in the manufacture of plastics, rubber and petrochemicals. It is also used as a refrigerant. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Most ammonia released to the environment comes from natural sources such as decaying organic matter, for example, animal manure. Man-made releases, such as from the use of fertilisers, waste disposal sites and industrial processes are much smaller in comparison. </text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to ammonia at normal background levels is unlikely to have an adverse effect to health.</text>
	<text>At high local concentrations (e.g. from decomposing manure) ammonia can cause harm to vegetation, but greater damage is from releases of aqueous ammonia to water bodies as it is very toxic to aquatic organisms. Ammonia releases to the environment contribute to both eutrophication and acidification of eco-systems. Emissions of ammonia to air can also contribute to the formation of particulate matter, an important pollutant in terms of its potential to harm human health.  </text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Gas</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-78</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>-33</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>7510</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>482000</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>0.23</partition_coeff>
    <ph>11.6</ph>
    <flammable_limits>16% - 25% </flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>11</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>651</autoignition_temp>
    <density>0.7</density>
    <vapour_density>0.588</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>350</toxicity>
    <description>Pure ammonia is a colourless, strong odour, corrosive gas which can be stored under high pressure as a liquid.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="6">
        <standard>EN ISO 11732:2005</standard>
        <title>Determination of ammonium nitrogen -- Method by flow analysis (CFA and FIA) and spectrometric detection</title>
        <target>Water Quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 3.4%</uncertainty>
	</provision>
      <provision id="6">
        <standard>No International reference for emissions to air</standard>
        <title>The 2009 EMEP/EEA air pollutant emission inventory guidebook provides information on calculating emissions.</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>-</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="7">
    <pollutant_name>Non-methane volatile organic compounds (NMVOC)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>The main sources of NMVOCs are the combustion of fossil fuels, solvents for industrial processes, paints and varnishes. Smaller amounts are released from dry cleaning, the beverage industry and farming.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Industrial emissions of VOCs arise from the evaporation of solvents, from accidental spillage or evaporation of petroleum products.</text>
	<text>Natural sources of NMVOCs are primarily emissions from forests.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Many NMVOCs react with other air pollutants to form ground-level ozone an important pollutant at local and global scales. Elevated levels of ozone can cause respiratory health problems and can lead to premature mortality. High levels of ozone also damage plants, reducing agricultural crop yields and decreasing forest growth.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <description> </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="7">
        <standard>EN 13649:2001</standard>
        <title>Determination of the mass concentration of individual gaseous organic compounds - Activated carbon and solvent desorption method</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, at a 95% level of confidence, ranges between ± 4 mg/m<sup>3</sup> and ± 11 mg/m<sup>3</sup>, depending on sampling procedure, analyse and concentration</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="8">
    <pollutant_name>Nitrogen dioxides (NOX/NO2)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Nitrogen dioxide is used in various chemical processes as an oxidising agent, including the production of nitric acid.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Fuel combustion, biomass burning and various production processes are the major releases of nitrogen oxides. Minor natural sources are from lightning, natural fires and various biological processes.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>At low concentrations, nitrogen-containing species deposited on plants can act as nutrients. </text>
	<text>Nitrogen oxides may contribute to acid deposition and also to eutrophication.  Of the chemical species that comprise the NOx air pollutant, it is NO2 that is associated with adverse effects on health, as high concentrations cause inflammation of the airways. NOx also contributes to the formation of harmful particulate matter and ground level ozone in the atmosphere. Nitrogen dioxide can react with organic peroxy radicals (formed from the breakdown of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) in the air) to form PANs (peroxyacetyl nitrates), which can serve as a temporary reservoir for reactive nitrogen and may be transported long distances.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Gas</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-9.3</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>21.15 </boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>720</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>Soluble</water_solubility>
    <vapour_density>1.58</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>220</toxicity>
    <description>Nitrogen dioxide is a reddish-brown gas with a strong odour, although its colour can only be seen at high concentrations.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="8">
        <standard>EN 14792:2005</standard>
        <title>Determination of mass concentration of nitrogen oxides. Method: chemiliuminescence</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, at a 95% level of confidence, is ± 17 mg/m<sup>3</sup> for values about 200 mg/m<sup>3</sup></uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="8">
        <standard>ISO 11564:1998</standard>
        <title>Determination of the mass concentration of nitrogen oxides – Method: Naphthylethylenediamine photometric method</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty ranges between ± 3 mg/m<sup>3</sup> for values about 50 mg/m<sup>3</sup> and ± 12.2 mg/m<sup>3</sup> for values about 420 mg/m<sup>3</sup></uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="8">
        <standard>ISO 10849:1996</standard>
        <title>Determination of the mass concentration of nitrogen oxides. Method: Performance characteristics of automated measuring systems</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, reported with a 95% level of confidence, is less than 10% of full scale</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="9">
    <pollutant_name>Perfluorocarbons (PFCs)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Used for the manufacture of semi-conductors and refrigerants. Occasional use includes environmental tracer gases, fire extinguishers and a number of medical and cosmetic applications.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Major releases are from the semiconductor industry, refrigeration sector (blending, filling, leakage and end of life destruction of equipment). There are no natural sources of PFC's </text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>At the low concentrations that are found in the environment, PFCs are not considered harmful to human health. </text>
	<text>PPFCs are greenhouse gases controlled under the UNFCCC’s Kyoto protocol. They typically have a high global warming potential over a 100 year time horizon (7000-10000 times that of carbon dioxide according to the IPCC 4th assessment report) but are generally released only in relatively small amounts to the environment. PFCs can persist for thousands of years.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Gas</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-147.6</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>-36.6</boiling_point>
    <flash_point>Non flammable</flash_point>
    <vapour_density>1.29</vapour_density>
    <mutagenicity>Negative</mutagenicity>
    <description>Perfluorocarbons (PFC's) are a group of man-made chemicals consisting of carbon and fluorine which are colourless, odourless, unreactive and non-flammable gases.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
	  <provision id="9">
        <standard>No International standard for emissions to air</standard>
        <title>The 2006 IPCC Guidelines for National Greenhouse Gas Inventories provide information on calculating emissions (Volume 3)</title>
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
	</iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="10">
    <pollutant_name>Sulphur hexafluoride (SF6)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Main uses include electrical insulation and the manufacture of magnesium. Other uses include the manufacture of semiconductors, environmental tracer gases, and as a filler for cushioning in objects such as tennis balls.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Sulphur hexafluoride releases are expected from electrical substations, magnesium smelters and various consumer goods. Sulphur hexafluoride does not occur naturally in the environment.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>At the typical concentrations found in the environment, sulphur hexafluoride is not thought to affect human health. </text>
	<text>Sulphur hexafluoride is a greenhouse gas controlled under the UNFCCC’s Kyoto protocol.  It has a global warming potential 22,800 times that of carbon dioxide over a 100 year time horizon according to the IPCC 4th assessment report, however in absolute terms it is only released in small amounts. Due to its high stability, sulphur hexafluoride will remain in the atmosphere for thousands of years.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Gas</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-50.8</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>-63.8</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>90300</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>31</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>1.68</partition_coeff>
    <vapour_density>5.11</vapour_density>
    <description>Sulphur hexafluoride is an unreactive, non-toxic heavy gas (five times heavier than air)  with no colour or smell.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
	  <provision id="10">
        <standard>No International standard for emissions to air</standard>
        <title>The 2006 IPCC Guidelines for National Greenhouse Gas Inventories provide information on calculating emissions (Volume 3)</title>
        <target>-</target>
        <uncertainty>-</uncertainty>
      </provision>
	</iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="11">
    <pollutant_name>Sulphur oxides (SOx/SO2)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Sulphur dioxide is produced naturally by the burning of fossil fuels. Man-made uses include bleaching, fumigant and food preservative. Sulphur trioxide is used to produce sulphuric acid.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The main source of release is from the burning of coal and fuel. Large industrial plants and other industrial sites are responsible for approximately 90% sulphur dioxide released to the atmosphere. It is produced naturally by volcanoes and forest fires.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Background level exposures to sulphur oxide can harm sensitive individuals. Sulphur dioxide can contribute to acid deposition, the impacts of which can be significant, including adverse effects on aquatic ecosystems in rivers and lakes, and damage to forests. Acidic deposition can also harm monuments and buildings by increasing the rate of corrosion. </text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Gas</state>
    <melt_freeze_point> -75.5</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>-10</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>2432</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>Reacts with water.</water_solubility>
    <density>2.811</density>
    <vapour_density>2.263</vapour_density>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <description>Sulphur dioxide and sulphur trioxicde are the main sulphur oxides. Sulphur dioxide is a colourless gas with a pungent odour. Sulphur trioxide is a fuming colourless liquid. Data for sulphur dioxide is provided as an example. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="11">
        <standard>EN 14791:2005</standard>
        <title>Determination of mass concentration of sulphur dioxide - Reference method</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, reported with a 95% level of confidence, is ± 4.8 mg/m<sup>3</sup> for values about 15 mg/m<sup>3</sup></uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="11">
        <standard>ISO 7934:1989</standard>
        <title>Determination of the mass concentration of sulfur dioxide, hydrogen peroxide/barium perchlorate/Thorin method
Same principle of detection as EN 14791</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>The standard deviation reported ranges between ± 8.8 mg/m<sup>3</sup> for values about 16 mg/m<sup>3</sup> and ± 158 mg/m<sup>3</sup> for values about 2000 mg/m<sup>3</sup></uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="11">
        <standard>ISO 7935:1992</standard>
        <title>Determination of the mass concentration of sulfur dioxide; performance characteristics of automated measuring methods</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, at a 95% level of confidence, is less than 10% of full scale</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="11">
        <standard>ISO 11632:1998</standard>
        <title>Determination of mass concentration of sulfur dioxide - Ion chromatography method</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, at a 95% level of confidence ranges between ± 3.4 mg/m<sup>3</sup> for values about 6 mg/m<sup>3</sup> and ± 30 mg/m<sup>3</sup> for values about 333 mg/m<sup>3</sup></uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="12">
    <pollutant_name>Total nitrogen</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>The main use of substances that make up total nitrogen in soil and waters is fertilisers and manures.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Main releases are due to combustion processes which will form oxides of nitrogen. Oxides of nitrogen can also form naturally in thunderstorms and forest fires.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>As this is a diverse group of substances, related health effects will depend on the particular chemical. </text>
	<text>As soluble nitrogen compounds have the potential to be transported large distances, they can cause acidification and eutrophication in regions thousands of miles away from their release point. Increased amounts of nitrogen compounds in waters can result in increased growth rates of algal species which in turn can lead to oxygen depletion and blocking of sunlight in water bodies and hence altering ecosystem balances.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>169</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>decomposes</boiling_point>
    <water_solubility>213000</water_solubility>
    <ph>5.4</ph>
    <flammable_limits>non flammable</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>decomposes</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>decomposes</autoignition_temp>
    <density>1.72</density>
    <description>Nitrogen gas is relatively non-reactive and makes up 80% of the atmosphere. Total nitrogen is a term used in the measurement of organic and inorganic nitrogen compounds in soil and water. Ammonium nitrate data is provided as an example of a typical nitrogen compound. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="12">
        <standard>EN 12260:2003</standard>
        <title>Determination of nitrogen – Determination of bound nitrogen (TNb), following oxidation to nitrogen oxides</title>
        <target>Water Quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 9.8%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="12">
        <standard>EN ISO 11905-1:1998</standard>
        <title>Determination of nitrogen - Part 1: Method using oxidative digestion with peroxodisulfate (ISO 11905-1:1997)</title>
        <target>Water Quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 6.5%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="13">
    <pollutant_name>Total phosphorus</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Phosphoric acid is used to make phosphates. Other uses include sugar refining for drinks, fertilisers, water softeners and detergents.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Phosphates are released through using fertilisers, human sewage and industrial use of detergents. Phosphorous compounds also occur naturally in all living organisms.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to typical environmental concentrations of phosphorus-containing compounds is unlikely to harm human health, but large quantities of phosphates in the aquatic environment can contribute to eutrophication. Phosphate pollution can persist for long time periods within aquatic environments. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>416</melt_freeze_point>
    <vapour_pressure>27300</vapour_pressure>
    <autoignition_temp>260</autoignition_temp>
    <density>2.34</density>
    <vapour_density>4.77</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>3.03</toxicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Lepomis macrochirus - 0.005 mg/l - 96 hPimephales promelas - 0.020 - 0.2 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 0.03 mg/l - 48 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Total phosphorus is a term used in the measurement of organic and inorganic phosphorus compounds in soil and water. Compounds of phosphorus occur in many forms, e.g. Colourless liquid (phosphoric acid) and white solid (potassium phosphate). The data given refers to red phosphorus.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="13">
        <standard>EN ISO 15681-1:2004</standard>
        <title>Determination of orthophosphate and total phosphorus contents by flow analysis (FIA and CFA) - Part 1: Method by flow injection analysis (FIA) (ISO 15681-1:2003)</title>
        <target>Water Quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 7.5%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="13">
        <standard>EN ISO 15681-2:2004</standard>
        <title>Determination of orthophosphate and total phosphorus contents by flow analysis (FIA and CFA) - Part 2: Method by continuous flow analysis (CFA) (ISO 15681-1:2003)</title>
        <target>Water Quality</target>
       <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 13.6%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="13">
        <standard>EN ISO 11885:2009</standard>
        <title>Determination of 33 elements by inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectroscopy (ISO 11885:2007)</title>
        <target>Water Quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 7.4%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="13">
        <standard>EN ISO 6878:2004</standard>
        <title>Determination of phosphorus - Ammonium molybdate spectrometric method (ISO 6878:2004)</title>
        <target>Water Quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 8 and 12%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="14">
    <pollutant_name>Hydrochlorofluorocarbons (HCFCs)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>The main uses of HCFCs are as refrigerants and in the production of foam materials.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Releases of HCFCs will be from leakages in refrigeration and air conditioning appliances. There are no natural sources.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to HCFCs at normal background levels is unlikely to have an adverse effect to health.</text>
	<text>Although not likely to impact the environment on a local scale, HCFC releases to the environment have serious environmental consequences at a global level by contributing to destruction of the stratospheric ozone layer. Although the amounts emitted are relatively small, HCFCs are also potent greenhouses in their own right and thus also contribute to climate change.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Gas</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-157.4</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>-40.8</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>7250</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>2770</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>1.08</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>Non flammable</flammable_limits>
    <vapour_density>3.07</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>220000</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <description>Hydrochlorofluorocarbons (HCFCs) are non-flammable gases or liquids which will evaporate easily. Data from Monochlorodifluoromethane is provided as an example.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
	  <provision id="14">
        <standard>No International standard for emissions to air.</standard>
        <title>2006 IPCC Guidelines for National Greenhouse Gas Inventories (Volume 3) </title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
	</iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="15">
    <pollutant_name>Chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>CFCs used to be used as the propellant in aerosol sprays and as refrigerants, although this is banned in most parts of the world under the Montreal Protocol.  Other former uses included the production of foam materials and cleaning solvents.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The main release of CFCs is from aerosols containing the gas, refrigeration appliances and some foam materials. </text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to chlorofluorocarbons at normal background levels is unlikely to have any adverse effect on human health.</text>
	<text>Although not likely to impact the environment on a local scale, CFC releases to the environment have serious environmental consequences at a global level by contributing to destruction of the stratospheric ozone layer. Although the amounts emitted are relatively small, CFCs are also potent greenhouses in their own right and thus also contribute to climate change.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Gas</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-158</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>-29.8</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>4850</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>Soluble</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>2.16</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>Non flammable</flammable_limits>
    <density>1.486</density>
    <vapour_density>4.1</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>&gt;1000</toxicity>
    <mutagenicity>Negative </mutagenicity>
    <description>Chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs) are colourless, non-flammable inert gases or liquids that evaporate rapidly. They contain chlorine, fluorine and carbon. Data for dichlorodifluoromethane is provided as an example.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
	  <provision id="15">
        <standard>No International standard for emissions to air.</standard>
        <title>2006 IPCC Guidelines for National Greenhouse Gas Inventories (Volume 3) </title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>-</uncertainty>
      </provision>
	</iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="16">
    <pollutant_name>Halons</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Although the use of halons has been phased out, previous uses include fire suppressants and fire extinguishers.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Small amounts of halons have been released via their use as fire extinguishers. There are no natural sources.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Although not likely to impact the environment on a local scale, halon releases to the environment have serious environmental consequences at a global level by contributing to destruction of the stratospheric ozone layer. Although the amounts emitted are relatively small, halons are also potent greenhouses in their own right and thus also contribute to climate change.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-110.32</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>47.3</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>325</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>3</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>2.96</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>Not flammable</flammable_limits>
    <density>2.149</density>
    <description>Halons are chemicals similar to CFCs, but will have at least one atom of bromine. They are inert colourless gases or liquids which will evaporate rapidly.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="16">
        <standard>EN ISO 7393-1, 2, 3:2000</standard>
        <title>Determination of free chlorine and total chlorine by titration (Pt 1), colorimetric method (Pt 2), iodometric titration (Pt 3).
ISO 7393-1,2:1985, ISO 7393-3:1990)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 0.1 and 0.4 mg/l</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="17">
    <pollutant_name>Arsenic and compounds (as As)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Arsenic compounds are mainly used in agricultural pesticides and wood preservatives. They are also used in glass, metal alloys, bronzing and in pyrotechnics. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The main source of arsenic compounds into the environment is from burning fossil fuels in power stations. They are also released through their use in pesticides and wood preservatives. Arsenic occurs naturally in the environment and it is found in soils, rocks and ground water. </text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Arsenic persists in the environment, accumulates in living organisms and at high concentrations is toxic to wildlife. </text>
	<text>Long term exposure to certain arsenic compounds may cause skin and lung cancer. Direct contact with skin can cause burning and irritation. However the extent of harmful effects following exposure to arsenic compounds depends upon both the form and bioavailability of arsenic. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <boiling_point>Sublimes</boiling_point>
    <water_solubility>Insoluble</water_solubility>
    <density>5.72</density>
    <toxicity>763</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>1</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <description>Arsenic is a grey coloured solid which shows properties that are partly metallic and partly non-metallic. Inorganic compounds of arsenic usually colourless solids with variable solubility in water. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="17">
        <standard>EN 14385:2004</standard>
        <title>Determination of the total emission of As, Cd, Cr, Co, Cu, Mn, Ni, Pb, Sb, TI and V</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Uncertainties not quoted in the standard</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="17">
        <standard>EN ISO 11969:1996</standard>
        <title>Determination of arsenic - Atomic absorption spectrometric method (hydride technique) (ISO 11969:1996)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 7.1%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="17">
        <standard>EN 26595:1992</standard>
        <title>Determination of total arsenic; silver diethyldithiocarbamate spectrophotometric method (ISO 6595:1982)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
       <uncertainty>-</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="18">
    <pollutant_name>Cadmium and compounds (as Cd)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Cadmium is used in a variety of ways. It is used in batteries (Nickel Cadmium), corrosion resistant metal plating, pigments and plastics and low melting point metal alloys. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>It is mostly released during metal processing (e.g. zinc, aluminium, iron and steel) and during the recycling of batteries. It is also released during the combustion of fossil fuels in power stations. </text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>ECadmium is readily accumulated by many organisms - particularly by micro-organisms and molluscs and is easily concentrated in the food chain. It can have a wide range of toxic effects on plants and animals. Mostly the effects are on growth and reproduction and occur only following moderate or high exposures during long periods.  </text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>321.07</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>767</boiling_point>
    <water_solubility>Insoluble</water_solubility>
    <density>8.65</density>
    <toxicity>225</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>1</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Positive</mutagenicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Oncorhynchus tshawytscha - 0.0011 mg/l 96h </aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 0.0007 mg/l - 21 d</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Cadmium is a soft silvery metal which occurs in nature in mineral form with other elements such as oxygen, chlorine and sulphur.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="18">
        <standard>EN 14385:2004</standard>
        <title>Determination of the total emission of As, Cd, Cr, Co, Cu, Mn, Ni, Pb, Sb, TI and V</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="18">
        <standard>EN ISO 5961:1995</standard>
        <title>Determination of cadmium by atomic absorption spectrometry (ISO 5961:1994)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 26.2%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="18">
        <standard>EN ISO 11885:2009</standard>
        <title>Determination of 33 elements by inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectroscopy (ISO 11885:2007)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 6.8%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="19">
    <pollutant_name>Chromium and compounds(as Cr)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Chromium is an important component of stainless steel and high performance alloys. It is also used in furnace bricks, dyes and pigments and  chrome plating,  chemical catalyst, leather tanning, wood preservative. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Most sources of chromium emissions to the environment are from chemical manufacturing, the combustion of fossil fuels, waste incineration and steel making. A smaller source is glass production.</text>
	<text>	Chromium is also released naturally from the earth's crust.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Pure chromium metal and alloys are not hazardous to health. Exposure to low levels of chromium compounds in the environment is not likely to affect health. No significant effects on the global environment are expected due to chromium releases. </text>
	<text>In the environment, chromium compounds may be toxic to some species of wildlife. Some aquatic species (but not fish) accumulate chromium and therefore the metal concentrates up the food chain. The level of toxicity of chromium is very dependent of its oxidation state; chromium (VI) compounds are more readily absorbed and more highly toxic than chromium (III) compounds.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>1907</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>2671</boiling_point>
    <water_solubility>Insoluble</water_solubility>
    <density>7.15</density>
    <carcinogenicity>3 [Cr and Cr (III) compounds], 1 [Cr (VI) compounds]</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Positive</mutagenicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Salmo gairdneri - 4.4 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Chromium is a hard, steel-grey coloured metal which has a high melting point and can take a high polish. Compounds of chromium are usually highly coloured. This metal has a high corrosion resistance and hardness.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="19">
        <standard>EN 14385:2004</standard>
        <title>Determination of the total emission of As, Cd, Cr, Co, Cu, Mn, Ni, Pb, Sb, TI and V</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="19">
        <standard>EN 1233:1997</standard>
        <title>Determination of chromium - Atomic absorption spectrometric methods</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 37%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="19">
        <standard>EN ISO 11885:2009</standard>
        <title>Determination of 33 elements by inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectroscopy (ISO 11885:2007)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 5.6%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="20">
    <pollutant_name>Copper and compounds (as Cu)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Copper is widely used to make electrical wires, electrical and electronic applications, water pipes and heat exchangers. Copper compounds are used in wood preservatives, boat anti-fouling paints and agricultural chemicals. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Most releases of copper are through the burning of fossil fuels in power plants, metal production, waste incinerators, sewage treatment and through the application of agricultural chemicals. Copper occurs naturally in the environment. </text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text> Exposure to small amounts of copper in drinking water and food is common in nature and thus such levels are unlikely to have adverse effects on health. However, local emissions leading to abnormal levels of copper may have environmental and health consequences. At this local scale, copper can accumulate in some organisms and at high concentrations has toxic effects on some species of aquatic life and certain soil micro-organisms potentially disrupting nutrient cycling processes. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Soild</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>1084.62</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>2562</boiling_point>
    <water_solubility>Insoluble</water_solubility>
    <density>8.96</density>
    <toxicity>&gt;5000 </toxicity>
    <mutagenicity>Positive</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Oncorhynchus kisutch - 0.017 mg/l - 96 h </aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 0.035 mg/l - 21 d</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Copper is a reddish brown metal that is an excellent conductor of electricity and heat. Copper compounds are usually blue or green in colour. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="20">
        <standard>EN 14385:2004</standard>
        <title>Determination of the total emission of As, Cd, Cr, Co, Cu, Mn, Ni, Pb, Sb, TI and V</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="20">
        <standard>EN ISO 11885:2009</standard>
        <title>Determination of 33 elements by inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectroscopy</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 4 and 11%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="21">
    <pollutant_name>Mercury and compounds (as Hg)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Metallic mercury is used in thermometers, dental fillings and batteries and is used to manufacture chlorine gas and caustic soda. Mercury vapour is used in fluorescent lamps. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Mercury is released into the environment from a number of sources including waste incineration, its use in manufacturing, from batteries, metal production and coal combustion. It is also released from its use in dental surgeries, from crematoria and from hospitals. </text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Because of the persistence, ability to undergo long-range transport and the bioaccumulation potential of mercury and its compounds in the environment, mercury is regarded as a globally important pollutant. </text>
	<text>Exposure usually occurs through consumption of contaminated fish or grain and may be carcinogenic. The human nervous system is very sensitive to mercury in all forms. Inhaling mercury vapour or methyl mercury is more harmful than inhaling other forms because more mercury can reach the brain. 

Mercury and mercury compounds are toxic to wildlife, plants and micro-organisms. Organo-mercury compounds are accumulated by some species in the aquatic environment and low levels of mercury can build up to high levels in insects, birds and fish.
</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-38.83</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>356.73</boiling_point>
    <water_solubility>Insoluble</water_solubility>
    <density>13.5336</density>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Lepomis macrochirus - 0.16 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 0.0067 mg/l - 21 d</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Mercury is a silver coloured metal which is liquid at room temperature and is odourless and non-flammable. Mercury combines with other elements such as chlorine, sulphur and oxygen to form inorganic salts which are usually white powders or crystals. Mercury also combines with carbon to form organo-mercury compounds, which are much more hazardous than elemental mercury.  </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="21">
        <standard>EN 13211:2001</standard>
        <title>Stationary source emissions - Manual method of determination of the concentration of total mercury</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, reported with a 95% level of confidence, ranges between ± 2.5 μg/m<sup>3</sup> for values at about 4 μg/m<sup>3</sup> and ± 26 μg/m<sup>3</sup> for values about 100 μg/m<sup>3</sup></uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="21">
        <standard>EN 14884:2005</standard>
        <title>Determination of total mercury: Automated measuring systems</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="21">
        <standard>EN 1483:2007</standard>
        <title>Determination of mercury – Method using atomic absorption spectrometry</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 23.7%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="21">
        <standard>EN 12338:1998</standard>
        <title>Determination of mercury – Methods after enrichment by amalgamation</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 28.9%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="21">
        <standard>EN 17852:2008</standard>
        <title>Determination of mercury - Method using atomic fluorescence spectrometry (ISO 17852:2006)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 19.8%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="22">
    <pollutant_name>Nickel and compounds (as Ni)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Nickel is used in the manufacture of steel and other alloys. It is used extensively in batteries, in chemical, petroleum and electrical industries. It is also used in ceramics and electroplating.  </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Releases of Nickel into the environment mostly come from the burning of fossil fuels,  mining and refining processes and from waste incineration. Nickel occurs naturally in the environment in small amounts.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Releases of nickel are unlikely to have an immediate effect on the local and global environment. Very small amounts of nickel have been shown to be essential for normal growth and reproduction in some species of animals and plants. 

The most common health effect of nickel is an allergic reaction following prolonged contact with the metal (e.g. with jewellery or coins) with some people (about 10-20%) becoming sensitive to it and developing skin rashes and, more rarely, asthma. Once a person has become sensitive further contact with the metal will produce a reaction. </text>
	<text>Chronic inhalation exposure to nickel fumes may cause cancer. 

Nickel can accumulate in soils and sediments and may ultimately affect water quality. It does not appear to accumulate in fish, plants or animals used for food. </text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>1455</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>2913</boiling_point>
    <water_solubility>Insoluble</water_solubility>
    <density>8.9</density>
    <carcinogenicity>2B [Nickel metal and alloy]  Group 1 [Nickel compounds]</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Salmo gairdneri - 17.1 mg/l - 96 h  </aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 0.095 mg/l - 21 d</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Nickel is a white, silvery hard metal with magnetic properties. Nickel compounds are often green in colour.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="22">
        <standard>EN 14385:2004</standard>
        <title>Determination of the total emission of As, Cd, Cr, Co, Cu, Mn, Ni, Pb, Sb, TI and V</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="22">
        <standard>EN ISO 11885:2009</standard>
        <title>Determination of 33 elements by inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectroscopy (ISO 11885:2007)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 5.1%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="23">
    <pollutant_name>Lead and compounds (as Pb)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Lead is used in lead-acid batteries, as a roofing material, in solders in electrical systems and as radiation shielding. In the past it was widely used in plumbing and as  additive in paints and petrol. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Man-made releases of lead come mostly from metal production and processing, from the burning of fossil fuels in power stations and from the chemical industry. A significant amount of lead used to be released from the use of lead in petrol, lead paints and plumbing, though this has decreased rapidly as these uses have been phased out. </text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Lead is a cumulative poison which affects the central nervous system. Low levels of exposure to lead can also cause harm to the unborn child and to the development of the brain in children, damage the male reproductive system and is potentially carcinogenic. </text>
	<text>Lead is found in the environment in soils and sediments. Its solubility increases in soft, acidic water. Lead is toxic to plants and animals when they are exposed to high levels. However, no significant effects on the global environment are expected. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>327.5</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>1749</boiling_point>
    <water_solubility>Insoluble</water_solubility>
    <density>11.3</density>
    <carcinogenicity>2B [Lead metal]  Group 2A [ Lead compounds]</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Positive</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistant</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Colisa fasciata - 26 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 0.1 mg/l - 21 d</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Lead is a bluish-white very dense metal which is very soft, highly malleable and ductile.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="23">
        <standard>EN 14385:2004</standard>
        <title>Determination of the total emission of As, Cd, Cr, Co, Cu, Mn, Ni, Pb, Sb, TI and V</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="23">
        <standard>EN ISO 11885:2009</standard>
        <title>Determination of 33 elements by inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectroscopy (ISO 11885:2007)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 7.2%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="24">
    <pollutant_name>Zinc and compounds (as Zn)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Zinc is used in batteries, in alloys such as brass and bronze and provides a corrosion resistant coating for other metals (e.g. galvanised steel). It is also used in the manufacture of paints, plastics, rubber tyres, dyes, wood preservatives and cosmetics. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Most releases of zinc to the environment are from metal production processes, combustion of coal in power stations, waste incineration and from the wear of vehicle tyres. </text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Zinc is an essential nutrient in the diet. Exposure to potentially harmful levels usually occurs only through drinking of contaminated water (due to zinc water pipes or accidental industrial releases). Harmful effects following exposure include nausea and stomach cramps. </text>
	<text>Local releases of zinc can build up in fish and other aquatic organisms and poison the animals that eat them. Emissions of zinc are rarely large enough to cause these damaging levels.  </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>419.5</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>907</boiling_point>
    <water_solubility>Insoluble</water_solubility>
    <density>7.14</density>
    <persistence>Persistant</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Salmo gairdneri - 0.8 mg/l - 96 h  </aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 0.1 mg/l - 21 d</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Zinc is a blue/white shiny metal. It is brittle and conducts electricity reasonably well. Compounds of zinc are often highly coloured. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="24">
        <standard>EN ISO 11885:2009</standard>
        <title>Determination of 33 elements by inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectroscopy (ISO 11885:2007)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 5.9%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="25">
    <pollutant_name>Alachlor</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Alachlor is a herbicide from the chloroacetanilide chemical family used to control growth rate of grasses. Since 2006, the use of alachlor as a herbicide has been banned in the European Union (Decision 2006/966/EC) </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Alachlor has entered the environment mainly as a result of its use as a pesticide.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to normal background levels of alachlor is unlikely to have any adverse effect. 
When released into soil or water, alachlor can be rapidly broken down by bacteria and sunlight. Alachor is not adsorbed by soil materials and this leads to its filtration into ground water. Once alachlor reaches ground water, it will disappear slowly. Alachlor does not tend to bio-accumulate in aquatic organisms or in plants and animals. </text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>40-41</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>378.17</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>15001</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>170.31</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>3.52</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>137</flash_point>
    <density>1.133</density>
    <toxicity>1200</toxicity>
    <mutagenicity>Negative</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Pimephales promelas - 5 mg/l</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Alachlor is a odourless, colourless to white crystalline solid .</description>
   <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="25">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title />
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="26">
    <pollutant_name>Aldrin</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Aldrin is a pesticide used to control soil insects and to protect wooden structures. Its use is now banned in the European Union under the Aarhus Protocol of the CLRTAP (Convention on Long-range Transboundary Air Pollution), but still used in some developing countries.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>In countries where the pesticide is used, it directly contaminates soils. There are no natural sources of aldrin.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to aldrin at normal levels is unlikely to have an adverse effect on human health. Dermal irritation is expected after prolonged contact.</text>
	<text>Aldrin is highly toxic to waterfowl and birds via ingestion of plants grown in contaminated soils or contaminated aquatic organisms. A variety of species have been known to be totally wiped out within an effected area. Plants and animals convert aldrin to dieldrin, which can travel large distances within the environment. Moreover, like related polychlorinated pesticides, aldrin is highly lipophilic, which contributes to its persistence in environmental media.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>104</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>384.9</boiling_point>
    <water_solubility>170</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>6.5</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>186.1</flash_point>
    <density>1.73</density>
    <toxicity>39</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Pimephales promelas -  0.0026 mg/l</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Aldrin is a white odourless crystalline solid in its pure form. Less pure forms are tan to dark brown with a mild odour.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="26">
        <standard>EN ISO 6468:1996</standard>
        <title>Determination of certain organochlorine insecticides, polychlorinated biphenyls and chlorobenzenes - Gas-chromatographic method after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 6468:1996)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 12 and 40%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="27">
    <pollutant_name>Atrazine</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Atrazine is a selective triazine herbicide which has been used to control residual weeds within crops.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Atrizine's main release is to soils and surface waters because of its route of application as a herbicide. Atrizine is not believed to occur naturally.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to atrazine at normal levels is unlikely to have an adverse effect on human health. Dermal contact will cause irritation and sensitisation after prolonged contact.</text>
	<text>Although no significant global impacts are considered to be likely, atrazine is considered to be dangerous to the environment and very toxic to aquatic organisms. It accumulates only slightly in fish. Atrazine can contaminate groundwaters and is very persistent in soils.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>175.8</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>205</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>289</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>33</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>2.5</partition_coeff>
    <dissocation_const>1.7</dissocation_const>
    <ph>7 (22C)</ph>
    <flash_point>176.7</flash_point>
    <density>1.23</density>
    <vapour_density>7.4</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>1869-3090</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Positive</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Pimephales promelas-  4.5-11 mg/l, </aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Atrazine is found as a white crystalline solid which will dissolve in water and organic solvents.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="27">
        <standard>EN ISO 10695:2000</standard>
        <title>Determination of selected organic nitrogen and phosphorus compounds - Gas chromatographic methods (ISO 10695:2000)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 12 and 19%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="28">
    <pollutant_name>Chlordane</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Chlordane is used on agricultural crops as a contact insecticide. Its use has been banned in the EU under the Aarhus Protocol of the CLRTAP (Convention on Long-range Transboundary Air Pollution).</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Chlordane will enter the environment through its use as a pesticide on crops. Other releases are through its manufacture, transportation and storage. There are no natural sources of chlordane to the environment.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Environmental exposure to chlordane is mostly thought to be through food as it has been found in meat, eggs and milk. Individuals exposed to high concentrations of chlordane may appear agitated or excited, but later may become depressed, uncoordinated, tired and confused. Minor changes in liver and kidney function could possibly occur from a long term exposure. Chlordane has also been identified as a possible carcinogen.  </text>
	<text>Chlordane is highly toxic to aquatic organisms and has the potential to cause adverse effects to the aquatic environment. It is thought to be an endocrine disruptor and neurotoxin to fish and rodents. 

It takes a very long time to break down in the environment, binds strongly to aquatic sediments, accumulates rapidly in many species and is semi-volatile.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>106-107</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>175</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.00000975</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.1</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>6.16</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>56</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>210</autoignition_temp>
    <density>1.59 - 1.63</density>
    <vapour_density>14</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>590</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B </carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Pimephales promelas - 0.09 mg/l</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description> Chlordane is a viscous amber liquid with a chlorine-like odour. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="28">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title />
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="29">
    <pollutant_name>Chlordecone</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Chlordecone has been used both as a fungicide and insecticide. Chlrodecone is also a degradation product of Mirex, an insecticide and fire retardant.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Chlordecone has entered the environment mainly as a result of its use as a pesticide, along with its release through the transportation, manufacture and storage of the product. There are no natural sources of chlordecone.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to chlordecone can occur through dermal contact, inhalation, or ingestion. Irritation to the eyes, nose and throat can occur following a short term exposure. Following long term exposure, harmful effects on the liver, nervous and reproductive system may occur.  </text>
	<text>Along with being very stable and persistent in the environment - binding strongly with soils and sediments, chlordecone is dangerous to aquatic life, toxic, and is also a carcinogen. It does not volatilise, but chlordecone adsorbed to dust particles can be found in the atmosphere.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>350</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>450.5</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.000000225</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>2.7</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>5.41</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>189.8</flash_point>
    <density>2.27</density>
    <vapour_density>16.94</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>95</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B </carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Negative</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Oncorhynchus Mykiss - 0.020 ppm - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Chlordecone is a stable, odourless white to tan coloured solid. Its solubility in organic solvents is high, but low in water.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="29">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title />
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="30">
    <pollutant_name>Chlorfenvinphos</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Chlorfenvinphos has been used as an organophosphorous pesticide for use on vegetables, cereals and seed treatments. It has also been used to fight malarial mosquitoes.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Chlorfenvinphos has entered the environment from its use as an insecticide. There are no natural sources of chlorfenvinphos.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to low levels of chlorvenfinphos over a long period of time is unlikely to cause harm to humans.  </text>
	<text>Chlorfenvinphos can be toxic to wildlife, but will decompose in soil and water to produce harmless products.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-23 - -19</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>167-170</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.0000075</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>124</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>3.85</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>&gt;285</flash_point>
    <density>1.36</density>
    <toxicity>10</toxicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Choerodon fasciata - &lt;0.32 mg/l</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Chlorfenvinphos is a colourless liquid with a mild odour. While miscible in a wide range of organic solvents, it is only partly soluble in water.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="30">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title />
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="31">
    <pollutant_name>Chloro-alkanes C10-C13</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Chloroalkanes are mainly used in industrial metal working fluids, for the cutting, drilling and machining of metals.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
		<text>Most releases to the environment of chloroalkanes were as the result of their manufacture and use as metal cutting fluids. There are no natural sources of chloroalkanes (C10-13).</text>
</main_methods_of_release>
<health_affects>
	<text>The effects on health of exposure to environment levels of these pollutants are unknown, although there is some scientific evidence that they may have carcinogenic effects. High levels of exposure to chloroalkanes (C10-13) can affect the kidneys, liver and thyroid. Chloroalkanes (C10-13) are not biodegradable and they bio-accumulate. They have been found in marine and freshwater life and in sediments. They are highly toxic to aquatic life.</text>
</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid</state>
    <boiling_point>&gt;200</boiling_point>
    <water_solubility>insoluble</water_solubility>
    <carcinogenicity>2B</carcinogenicity>
    <description>Chloroalkanes are short chain chlorinated paraffins, a group of chemicals containing carbon, hydrogen and chlorine. They are usually yellowish oily liquids with a faint odour.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="31">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title />
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="32">
    <pollutant_name>Chlorpyrifos</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Chlorpyrifos has been used as an organophosphorus pesticide for both private and commercial use. Chlorpyrifos has now been voluntarily removed for domestic use, but farmers still use it mixed with an oily liquid to control parasites and pests among crops and cattle. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Chlorpyrifos is released into the environment during its use as an insecticide. There are no natural sources of  chlorpyrifos.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to chlorpyrifos at normal background levels is unlikely to have any adverse effect on human health.

Exposure to chlorpyrifos such as following inhalation of air in an area that has been recently sprayed or through eating contaminated food can produce a variety of symptoms related to effects on the nervous system. The extent of the effects depends on the level of exposure but can include headaches, blurred vision, tearful eyes, excessive salivation, dizziness, confusion and muscle weakness or tremors. </text>
	<text>Chlorpyrifos can be toxic to wildlife and very toxic to aquatic organisms but only relatively small amounts enter surface waters and, since it does not dissolve well, most eventually evaporates from the surface. Chlorpyrifos does not tend to migrate from the area it is applied due to its ability to bind strongly to soil. It is also unlikely to seep into water bodies. 

Chlorpyrifos in soil, air or water is broken down by various processes - sunlight, bacterial action and chemical decomposition. It is therefore not considered likely that chlorpyrifos pollution has any effects on the global environment.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>42-43.5</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>160</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.0000202</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>1.4</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>4.7</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>181.1</flash_point>
    <density>1.48</density>
    <toxicity>135-163 </toxicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Pimephales promelas -  0.007-0.051 mg/l</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Chlorpyrifos is found as white crystals with a strong odour. While miscible in a wide range of organic solvents, it is not very soluble in water.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="32">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title />
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="33">
    <pollutant_name>DDT</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>DDT was used as an insecticide against a wide variety of pests, particularly for crop protection. Its use is banned in the EU under teh Aarhus Protocol of the CLRTAP (Convention on Long-range Transboundary Air Pollution), though it is still used in some developing countries for controlling insect borne diseases such as malaria.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>DDT entered the environment mainly as a result of its use as a pesticide. It is released, as well, as a result of losses during the manufacture process, transportation and storage.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to normal background levels of DDT is unlikely to have any adverse effects on human health. </text>
	<text>DDT is highly toxic to wildlife, particularly birds and fish. It concentrates, due to its stability, through the food chain with levels building up in fatty tissue. It is also highly persistent in the environment and is therefore classed as a persistent organic pollutant (POP). </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>108-109</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>260</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.00000016</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.0055</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>6.91</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>165</flash_point>
    <density>1.56</density>
    <toxicity>113-118 </toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B </carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <description>DDT is a crystalline solid with a slight odour normally presented as powder or crystals. This substance is very stable and dissolves in fats but not in water.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="33">
        <standard>EN ISO 6468:1996</standard>
        <title>Determination of certain organochlorine insecticides, polychlorinated biphenyls and chlorobenzenes - Gas-chromatographic method after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 6468:1996)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 12 and 40%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="34">
    <pollutant_name>1,2-dichloroethane (EDC)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>The main use of 1,2-dichloroethane is in the manufacture of other chemicals such as vinyl chloride, used to manufacture PVC. In the past it was used in domestic cleaning products and paint removers, and as a scavenger for lead in petrol. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
		<text>Most releases to the environment are from its use in chemical manufacture. Previously large quantities were release from leaded petrol. There are no natural sources. </text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to environment levels of 1,2-dichloroethane is unlikely to have adverse effects on health while long term exposure to higher levels can damage the nervous system, liver, kidneys and lungs. It can also exacerbate respiratory conditions such as asthma. 1,2-dichloroethane can accumulate in water bodies and persist in the environment for years. Large releases can be harmful to wildlife. As an air pollutant it can be involved in reactions with other substances to form harmful ground level ozone which can damage crops and human health.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-35</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>83.5</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>62.9</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>slightly miscible </water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>1.41</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>6.2%-16.2%</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>13</flash_point>
    <density>1.173</density>
    <toxicity>770</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Positive </mutagenicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Oncorhynchus mykiss - 225.00 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 540.00 mg/l - 24 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>1,2-dichloroethane is a clear, colourless and highly volatile liquid with a sweet smell.  It is highly flammable.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="34">
        <standard>EN ISO 10301:1997</standard>
        <title>Determination of highly volatile halogenated hydrocarbons - Gas-chromatographic methods (ISO 10301:1997)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 28.8%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="34">
        <standard>EN ISO 15680:2003</standard>
        <title>Gas-chromatographic determination of a number of monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, naphthalene and several chlorinated compounds using purge-and-trap and thermal desorption (ISO 15680:2003)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="35">
    <pollutant_name>Dichloromethane (DCM)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>The main uses of dichloromethane are in paint removers, aerosol solvents, in the manufacture of certain pharmaceuticals. It is also used as a degreasing agent in the electronics industries.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Most releases are through its use in industrial and domestic products. There are no natural sources of dichloromethane.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to environment levels of dichloromethane is unlikely to have significant effects on human health. Exposure to high levels can however cause damage to the nervous system, heart, kidneys, liver and may possibly cause cancer. In the environment it will slowly degrade following release to air, but may have some impact on local wildlife if released in large quantities. Releases to surface water may harm wildlife, but the effects will be reduced by rapid evaporation of dichloromethane into the air.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-95</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>39.6</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>448</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>slightly miscible </water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>1.25</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>12% - 19%</flammable_limits>
    <autoignition_temp>556.1</autoignition_temp>
    <density>1.252</density>
    <toxicity>1600</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Positive </mutagenicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Pimephales promelas - 193.00 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 1,682.00 mg/l - 48 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Dichloromethane is a clear, colourless liquid which is highly volatile and has a strong odour. It is non-flammable.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="35">
        <standard>EN ISO 10301:1997</standard>
        <title>Determination of highly volatile halogenated hydrocarbons - Gas-chromatographic methods (ISO 10301:1997)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 40 and 46%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="35">
        <standard>EN ISO 15680:2003</standard>
        <title>Gas-chromatographic determination of a number of monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, naphthalene and several chlorinated compounds using purge-and-trap and thermal desorption (ISO 15680:2003)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="36">
    <pollutant_name>Dieldrin</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>The main use of dieldrin is as an insecticide. Its use is banned in the EU under the Aarhus Protocol of the CLRTAP (Convention on Long-range Transboundary Air Pollution). </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Most releases of dieldrin were through its use as an insecticide. It is also formed in plants and animals from the breakdown of the closely related aldrin. </text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to dieldrin occurs mainly by ingestion of contaminated food, by dermal contact or by inhalation. Chronic exposure to low or moderate levels can cause headache, dizziness, irritability, vomiting and uncontrolled muscle movements.</text>
	<text>Exposure to high levels of dieldrin, typically in occupational settings, can cause convulsions and even death. Dieldrin is highly toxic to aquatic organisms, insects and other forms of wildlife. It accumulates in the environment, particularly in the fat of animals and strongly binds to soil particles. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>176</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>385</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.000000589</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.195</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>5.4</partition_coeff>
    <vapour_density>13.2</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>38.3</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <description>Dieldrin is a white or beige crystalline solid with a faint odour. It is closely related to other 'drin' pesticides, endrin, aldrin and isodrin. Its use is banned in the EU, though may still be used in some developing countries.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="36">
        <standard>EN ISO 6468:1996</standard>
        <title>Determination of certain organochlorine insecticides, polychlorinated biphenyls and chlorobenzenes - Gas-chromatographic method after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 6468:1996)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 12 and 40%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="37">
    <pollutant_name>Diuron</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Diuron has been used as a herbicide on agricultural land before crops emerge to interfere and improve growth. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Diuron will enter the environment through its use as a herbicide. There are no natural sources of diuron in the environment.</text>	
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to diuron at background levels is unlikely to effect human health. Over-exposure to diuron may have a harmful effect on the blood, and may cause cancer. </text>
	<text>Diuron is toxic to fish and aquatic invertebrates, but much less so to birds and bees. It is however classed as very toxic to aquatic organisms and may cause long-term effects on the aquatic environment. In the atmosphere diuron is broken down within days. In shallow surface waters, it will be broken down by sunlight in a matter of days. It will strongly bind to soil where it can remain for months or even years. It is not considered likely that diuron pollution has any significant harmful effects on the global environment. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>158-159</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>180-190</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.000000068</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>36.4</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>2.85</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>186.7</flash_point>
    <density>1.369</density>
    <vapour_density>8.04</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>&gt;3000</toxicity>
    <mutagenicity>Negative</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Pimephales promelas - 5.6 mg/l</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Diuron is in the form of white crystals with no odour. It will rapidly break down in hot water, acid, or alkaline solution.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="37">
        <standard>EN ISO 11369:1997</standard>
        <title>Determination of selected plant treatment agents - Method using high performance liquid chromatography with UV detection after solid-liquid extraction (ISO 11369:1997)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 20.3%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="38">
    <pollutant_name>Endosulphan</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Endosulphan is used as an insecticide and acaricide which control the numbers of insects and mites on crops.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Endosulphan will enter the environment through its use as a insecticide. There are no natural sources of endosulphan in the environment.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to endosulphan at background levels is unlikely to affect human health. Long-term exposure could potentially affect the blood, brain, eyes, immune system, lung, kidneys, liver, skin, and reproductive system. It may have endocrine disrupting effects. </text>
	<text>Endosulphan can be toxic to wildlife, particularly to fish, and build up in other living organisms. At high concentrations, endosulphan will harm plant life. It is also very persistent in the environment and binds tightly to soil. Significant leakage to ground waters is unlikely. Relatively small amounts of endosulfan may evaporate and will be broken down in air in a matter of hours.  It is not considered likely that endosulfan pollution has any effects on the global environment.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>70-106</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>449.7</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.0000062</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.33</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>3.83</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>225.8</flash_point>
    <density>1.94</density>
    <toxicity>18</toxicity>
    <description>Endosulphan is in the form of brown crystals with a slight odour. The product is a mixture of alpha and beta isomers.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="38">
        <standard>EN ISO 6468:1996</standard>
        <title>Determination of certain organochlorine insecticides, polychlorinated biphenyls and chlorobenzenes - Gas-chromatographic method after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 6468:1996)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 12 and 40%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="39">
    <pollutant_name>Endrin</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Endrin has been used as an insecticide on various crops. Its use has now been banned in the EU under the Aarhus Protocol of the CLRTAP (Convention on Long-range Transboundary Air Pollution). It is also banned in many other countries.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>In countries where the pesticide is used, it directly contaminates soils through its use as an insecticide. There are no natural sources of endrin.
	</text></main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to endrin at background levels is unlikely to effect human health. </text>
	<text>Endrin is toxic to wildlife, especially to aquatic organisms as it has a high potential to bioaccumulate. It binds tightly to soils and will persist for many years. Due to its ability to evaporate into the atmosphere and its stability in the environment, endrin has the potential to be transported great distances from the point of release, therefore causing concern at a local and global level. It is classified as a persistent organic pollutant (POP).</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>176</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>385</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.000003</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.25</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>5.2</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>1.1% - 7% </flammable_limits>
    <density>1.84</density>
    <toxicity>3</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 4.2 ug/l - 48 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Endrin in its pure form is white crystals with no odour. If endrin contains impurities, the crystals will be light brown in colour and have a slight chemical smell. Properties will be similar to that of dieldrin, aldrin and isodrin.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="39">
        <standard>EN ISO 6468:1996</standard>
        <title>Determination of certain organochlorine insecticides, polychlorinated biphenyls and chlorobenzenes - Gas-chromatographic method after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 6468:1996)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 12 and 40%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="40">
    <pollutant_name>Halogenated organic compounds (as AOX)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Most AOXs do not have a specific use and are not intentionally manufactured.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>A common source of AOXs is when chlorine containing bleaches and disinfectants come into contact with organic matter. A major source is from the manufacture of chlorine bleached white paper.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Halogenated organic compounds are a large and diverse group and adverse health effects are dependent on the particular compound involved.  </text>
	<text>Exposure to normal background levels is unlikely to have adverse health effects. Some adsorbable organic halogens (AOXs) are toxic to aquatic life, even at low concentrations. However, many AOX will persist in the environment with a tendency to bio-accumulate and concentrate up the food chain. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-63.41</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>61.17</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>158</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>7950</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>1.97</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>Not combustible</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>Not combustible</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>Not combustible</autoignition_temp>
    <density>1.4888</density>
    <vapour_density>4.12</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>50-500</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 79000 ug/l - 24 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Halogenated organic compounds (AOXs) are a large group of organic compounds that mostly contain chlorine, though some may contain iodine or bromine. The data given is for chloroform.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="40">
        <standard>EN ISO 9562:2004</standard>
        <title>Determination of adsorbable organically bound halogens (AOX) (ISO 9562:2004)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 12 and 19%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="41">
    <pollutant_name>Heptachlor</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Heptachlor has been used as a pesticide to kill insects in homes and on food crops.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Heptachlor will enter the air, soil, and groundwater from leaks at landfills and hazardous waste sites. There are no natural sources of heptachlor.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Harmful effects observed in animals include damage to the liver, increased excitement, and infertility. There are no reliable human studies, although heptachlor is classified as a possible human carcinogen.</text>
	<text>Heptachlor will bind to sediment and soil and will travel long distances through the atmosphere. Due to its highly stable structure, heptachlor can persist in the environment for decades. 

Like other POPs, heptachlor is lipophilic and poorly soluble in water and thus it tends to accumulate in the body fat of humans and animals.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>95-96</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>145</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.0003</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.18</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>6.1</partition_coeff>
    <density>1.57 - 1.59</density>
    <toxicity>40</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B </carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 -  Lepomis Macrochirus - 13 ug/ l- 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Isochrysis galbana - 157 ug/l/ - 96 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Heptachlor in its pure form is a white powder and the technical grade a tan colour with a camphor-like odour.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="41">
        <standard>EN ISO 6468:1996</standard>
        <title>Determination of certain organochlorine insecticides, polychlorinated biphenyls and chlorobenzenes - Gas-chromatographic method after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 6468:1996)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 12 and 40%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="42">
    <pollutant_name>Hexachlorobenzene (HCB)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Hexachlorobenzene (HCB) was used as a fungicide on seeds to protect against the fungal disease 'bunt' which affects cereal crops. Its use as a fungicide is banned in the EU under the Aarhus Protocol of the CLRTAP (Convention on Long-range Transboundary Air Pollution). HCB is also used in the manufacture of chlorinated organic solvents. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Hexachlorobenzene is released to the environment as a bi-product of the burning of coal, waste incineration and some metal processes. It has also been released through its use as a fungicide. It may also be released naturally from fires and volcanoes.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to HCB can occur through inhalation of polluted air or through eating contaminated food. However, the environment levels are not typically high enough to cause significant effects. At high levels of exposure, typically in occupational settings, HCB can damage the liver, the immune and the reproductive systems and induce birth defects. HCB is classed as dangerous to the environment. The main concern over environmental releases is related to its persistence and ability to bio-accumulate in the food chain. High levels can build up in fish and marine mammals and also certain plants.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Crystalline solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>227-229</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>323 - 326</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.000035</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.1922</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>4.89</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>243</flash_point>
    <density>2.075</density>
    <toxicity>10000</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Equivocal </mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Lepomis macrochirus - 7.6 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - &gt; 0.005 mg/l - 48 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Pure hexachlorobenzene (HCB) is a white crystalline solid with an unpleasant smell and is quite volatile. It is virtually insoluble in water, but readily dissolves in organic solvents, fats and oils.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="42">
        <standard>EN ISO 6468:1996</standard>
        <title>Determination of certain organochlorine insecticides, polychlorinated biphenyls and chlorobenzenes - Gas-chromatographic method after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 6468:1996)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 12 and 40%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="43">
    <pollutant_name>Hexachlorobutadiene (HCBD)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>The main use of HCBD is in the chemical industry where it is used in the manufacture of lubricants and rubber compounds. It is also used as a heat transfer liquid and hydraulic fluid.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>HCBD is mostly released during its manufacture and disposal in waste incinerators or landfill. There are no natural sources of HCBD.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to typically-found levels in the environment is unlikely to affect health. Exposure to high levels of HCBD can cause liver and kidney damage and cause irritation. HCBD is toxic to aquatic organisms and plants. It has a potential to accumulate in soils, sediments and water bodies. It will accumulate in organisms, particularly fish and shellfish, and concentrate in the food chain.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-21</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>230.5</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.22</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>insoluble</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>4.72</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>92.2</flash_point>
    <density>1.746</density>
    <toxicity>270</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Positive</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <description>Hexachlorobutadiene (HCBD) is a  colourless, oily, non-flammable liquid with a strong smell. It easily evaporates, but does not dissolve in water.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="43">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title />
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="44">
    <pollutant_name>1,2,3,4,5,6-hexachlorocyclohexane (HCH)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>gamma-HCH is used as an insecticide for timber. The EU has agreed to remove all agricultural uses of lindane.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Hexachlorocyclohexane is released to the environment through its use as an insecticide (as lindane). There are no natural sources of hexachlorocyclohexane in the environment.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to background levels of HCH is unlikely to cause health problems. It is not known for certain whether or not HCH is carcinogenic. Most of the adverse human health effects reported for one of its specific forms (lindane) have been identified in operational settings (mainly in the agricultural context where it is mainly used). </text>
	<text>The release of gamma-HCH to aquatic systems will damage insects and fish. Gamma-HCH will also accumulate in the fatty tissue of fish and the environment, therefore gamma-HCH can travel great distances and cause effects far from point of contact.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>113</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>288</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.000033</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>8</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>4.26</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>157.5</flash_point>
    <density>1.675</density>
    <toxicity>76</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B </carcinogenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Oncorhynchus mykiss - 0.022-0.028 mg/l</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Algae 0.78 mg/l - 120 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>There are eight isomers, or forms, of HCH with the most common being gamma-HCH (lindane) because of its value as an insecticide.Pure lindane is a white solid with a slightly musty smell.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="44">
        <standard>EN ISO 6468:1996</standard>
        <title>Determination of certain organochlorine insecticides, polychlorinated biphenyls and chlorobenzenes - Gas-chromatographic method after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 6468:1996)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 12 and 40%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="45">
    <pollutant_name>Lindane</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Lindane is used as an insecticide for timber. The EU has agreed to remove all agricultural uses of lindane.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Lindane is released to the environment through its use as an insecticide. There are no natural sources of lindane.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Lindane is one specific form of HCH, the gamma-HCH. Exposure to background levels is unlikely to cause health problems. It is not known for certain whether or not lindane is carcinogenic. Most of the adverse human health effects reported for lindane have been related to agricultural uses and chronic, occupational exposure of seed treatment workers. </text>
	<text>The release of lindane to aquatic systems damages insects and fish. Lindane will also persist and accumulate in the fatty tissue of fish and the environment, therefore lindane can travel great distances and cause effects far from point of contact.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>112.5</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>323.4</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.000042</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>7.3</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>3.72</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>157.5</flash_point>
    <density>1.59</density>
    <toxicity>76</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B </carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Oncorhynchus mykiss - 0.022-0.028 mg/l</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Algae - 0.78 mg/l - 120 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Lindane is a slightly volatile, white solid with a slight musty odour.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="45">
        <standard>EN ISO 6468:1996</standard>
        <title>Determination of certain organochlorine insecticides, polychlorinated biphenyls and chlorobenzenes - Gas-chromatographic method after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 6468:1996)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 12 and 40%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="46">
    <pollutant_name>Mirex</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Mirex has been used as an insecticide and has been commonly used as a fire retardant.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Mirex was mostly released to the environment through its use as an insecticide.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Due to its chemical robustness and lipophilicity, mirex is bio-accumulative and will not break down readily in the environment. There is evidence of accumulation of mirex in aquatic and terrestrial food chains to harmful levels. Besides, being lipophilic, mirex is strongly adsorbed on sediments.</text>
	<text>Data on human health effects do not exist.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>485</melt_freeze_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.0000008</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.085</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>6.89</partition_coeff>
    <density>2.25</density>
    <toxicity>235</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B </carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Negative</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <description>Odourless white crystals.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="46">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title />
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="47">
    <pollutant_name>PCDD + PCDF (dioxins + furans) (as Teq)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>PCDDs and PCDFs have no uses outside of research and laboratory use and are not intentionally manufactured.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>PCDDs and PCDFs are formed by the combustion of fuels and wastes, processing of metals and the production of pulp and paper. They are also produced naturally in the environment, major sources being forest fires and volcanoes. </text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to normal background levels of dioxins and furans is unlikely to cause health problems. Exposure to higher levels may affect the heart, liver, immune system, skin, and thyroid gland. Some PCDDs and PCDFs may cause cancer and may affect the unborn child in low concentrations. PCDDs and PCDFs released to air will eventually be deposited on soil and/or waters. Livestock and wildlife can subsequently ingest them from soil and vegetation, with fish susceptible to uptake from aquatic sediments.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>305-306</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>decomposes</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.0000000015</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.0002</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>6.8</partition_coeff>
    <density>1.827</density>
    <toxicity>0.022</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>1</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Negative</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <description>Polychlorinated-p-dioxins (PCDDs) and the related furans (PCDFs) and chlorine containing compound commonly known as dioxins and furans. There are many hundreds of different dioxins. They are crystalline solids which dissolve in oils, fats and organic solvents but not readily in water. The data given is based on TCDD.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="47">
        <standard>EN 1948-1 to -3:2006</standard>
        <title>Determination of the mass concentration of PCDDs/PCDFs and dioxin-like PCBs – Part 1: Sampling of PCDDs/PCDFs. Part 2: Extraction and clean-up of PCDDs/PCDFs. Part 3: Identification and quantification of PCDDs/PCDFs</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, at a 95% level of confidence, is ± 0.05 ng I-TEQ/m<sup>3</sup> for values about 0.035 ng I-TEQ/ m<sup>3</sup></uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="47">
        <standard>ISO 18073:2004</standard>
        <title>Determination of tetra- to octa-chlorinated dioxins and furans - Method using isotope dilution HRGC/HRMS</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 8 and 14%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="48">
    <pollutant_name>Pentachlorobenzene</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Pentachlorobenzene is used as a fire retardant and is used in the manufacture of fungicides.  </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Pentachlorobenzene is released during the manufacture and use of fungicides which contain it and the manufacture and disposal of products which contain it as a fire retardant.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Short-term exposure to high levels of pentachlorobenzene can affect the central nervous system. Long-term exposure can affect the liver and kidneys and can cause tissue lesions. It may also cause toxic effects on human reproduction. Pentachlorobenzene is a persistent and bio-accumulative chemical substance that could have an immediate or long-term harmful effect on the environment. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>84.0 - 87.0</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>277</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.00783</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>1.33</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>5.17</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>131.6</flash_point>
    <density>1.678</density>
    <toxicity>1080</toxicity>
    <persistence>Persistant</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Lepomis macrochirus - 0.25 mg/l 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 5.28 mg/l - 48 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Pentachlorobenzene is  a white or colourless solid with a perceptible odour. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="48">
        <standard>EN ISO 6468:1996</standard>
        <title>Determination of certain organochlorine insecticides, polychlorinated biphenyls and chlorobenzenes - Gas-chromatographic method after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 6468:1996)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 12 and 40%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="49">
    <pollutant_name>Pentachlorophenol (PCP)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>PCP is mainly used as a wood preservative and biocide on masonry.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The major source of release to the environment is from timber and masonry that has been treated with PCP and from its manufacture. There are no natural sources.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to high levels of PCP could cause damage to the liver, kidneys, blood, lungs, nervous system, immune system and digestive system. PCP may also be carcinogenic and cause damage to the unborn child. PCP is toxic to wildlife and can accumulate in the environment.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>188</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>309.5</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.000349</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>14</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>5.12</partition_coeff>
    <dissocation_const>4.7</dissocation_const>
    <density>1.804</density>
    <vapour_density>9.2</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>146-210</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B</carcinogenicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Carassius auratus -  0.160 - 0.380 mg/l - 96h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Chlorella vulgaris - 10.3 mg/l - 96h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Pentachlorophenol (PCP) is usually found as grey or brown powder, beads or flakes. It is odourless and only slightly soluble in water. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="49">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title />
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="50">
    <pollutant_name>Polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>PCBs are used mainly as electrical insulating material in capacitors and transformers. They are also used as flame retardants.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The main source of releases have been from their manufacture and use. Also leakage during disposal of PCB containing equipment. There are no natural sources of PCBs.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Excessive exposure to PCBs may affect the brain, eyes, heart, immune system, kidneys, liver, reproductive system, skin, and thyroid gland. PCBs may cause cancer and affect the unborn child. PCBs are toxic to wildlife, particularly aquatic organisms. They can cause serious reproductive and developmental problems and damage to the immune system. PCBs are categorised as a persistent organic pollutant (POP). </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid</state>
    <boiling_point>436.6 </boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.000000204</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.7</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>7.1</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>223.1</flash_point>
    <density>1.3-1.8 </density>
    <toxicity>3980</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2A</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Negitive</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - &lt;1 mg/l - 96h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) are usually colourless or yellow oily liquids or solids. PCBs have no odour. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="50">
        <standard>EN 1948-1 to -3:2006</standard>
        <title>Determination of the mass concentration of PCDDs/PCDFs and dioxin-like PCBs – Part 1: Sampling of PCDDs/PCDFs. Part 2: Extraction and clean-up of PCDDs/PCDFs.  Part 3: Identification and quantification of PCDDs/PCDFs</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation for measurement ranges between about 20 – 50%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="50">
        <standard>CEN/TS 1948-4:2007</standard>
        <title>Determination of the mass concentration of PCDDs/PCDFs and dioxin-like PCBs - Part 4: Sampling and analysis of dioxin-like PCBs</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="50">
        <standard>EN ISO 6468:1996</standard>
        <title>Determination of certain organochlorine insecticides, polychlorinated biphenyls and chlorobenzenes - Gas-chromatographic method after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 6468:1996)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 12 and 40%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="51">
    <pollutant_name>Simazine</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Simazine's use as a herbicide controls germinating grasses and a variety of weeds. Its use has declined in recent years, especially for non-agricultural use.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The release of simazine to the environment is through its use as a herbicide. There are no natural sources of simazine.
</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to simazine at normal background levels is not believed to effect human health. Over-exposure may affect the skin and blood.</text>
	<text>Simazine in the atmosphere will deposit onto soil and water bodies. Some can also seep into ground waters, although this is limited by its relatively low solubility in water.  Simazine can persist in soils and waters for a considerable time and has been found far from its original point of release. It is therefore a product of concern at both a local and global level.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>225</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>365.8</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.00294</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>6.2</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>2.1</partition_coeff>
    <dissocation_const>1.62</dissocation_const>
    <flash_point>175</flash_point>
    <density>1.33</density>
    <toxicity>500-10,000</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Negative</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Oncorhynchus mykiss - &gt;100 mg/l</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Algae Scenedesmus subspicatus - 0.042 mg/l</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Simazine is a white or colourless crystalline powder that when mixed with air, can create an explosive dust.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="51">
        <standard>ISO 10695:2000</standard>
        <title>Determination of selected organic nitrogen and phosphorus compounds - Gas chromatographic methods (ISO 10695:2000)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 21 and 46%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="51">
        <standard>EN ISO 11369:1997</standard>
        <title>Determination of selected plant treatment agents - Method using high performance liquid chromatography with UV detection after solid-liquid extraction (ISO 11369:1997)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 23.3%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="52">
    <pollutant_name>Tetrachloroethylene (PER)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>The main use of tetrachloroethylene is as a dry-cleaning agent for textiles and fabrics. It is also used for metal degreasing and is used in some consumer products. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>PER is mostly released through its use in dry-cleaning and as a degreasing agent when it evaporates. There are no natural sources of PER. </text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to normal environmental concentrations of tetrachloroethylene is unlikely to damage health. Exposure to high levels may affect the brain, eyes, kidneys, liver, skin, and throat. It may also cause cancer. In the air it is broken down by sun-light or washed back into the soil or water by rain. PER released to water and soil readily evaporates into the air or is slowly broken down by micro-organisms.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>−22</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>119.1</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>14.49</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>206</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>3.4</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>27.4</flash_point>
    <density>1.653</density>
    <vapour_density>5.83</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>2630</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2A</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Positive</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Cyprinodon variegatus - 9.8 mg/l - 96 h  Lepomis macrochirus - 13 mg/l - 96 h Onchorhynchus mykiss - 4.9 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 Daphnia magna - 7.5 mg/l - 48 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Tetrachloroethylene (PER) is a colourless, highly volatile liquid that has a distinctive sweet smell. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="52">
        <standard>EN ISO 15680:2003</standard>
        <title>Gas-chromatographic determination of a number of monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, naphthalene and several chlorinated compounds using purge-and-trap and thermal desorption. (ISO 15680:2003)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="52">
        <standard>EN ISO 10301:1997</standard>
        <title>Determination of highly volatile halogenated hydrocarbons - Gas-chromatographic methods (ISO 10301:1997)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 40 and 50%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="53">
    <pollutant_name>Tetrachloromethane (TCM)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>TCM is used in the manufacture of other chemicals. In the past it was commonly used as a dry-cleaning agent, a degreasing agent, a fire extinguishant and a pesticide. These uses are now banned.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The major source of release of TCM is from industrial spillages and from landfill sites where waste containing TCM has been buried.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to normal environmental concentrations of TCM is unlikely to damage health. Exposure to higher levels of TCM can cause damage to the liver, kidneys, lungs and central nervous system. It is also a possible carcinogen. Releases of TCM rapidly evaporate into the air. Air-borne TCM is very stable in the lower atmosphere where it can persist for 30-50 years. When it reaches the upper atmosphere it breaks down to give chlorine which damages the stratospheric ozone layer. TCM is also a greenhouse gas, contributing to climate change. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-23</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>76.8</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>115</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>793</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>2.83</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>non flammable</flammable_limits>
    <autoignition_temp>1000</autoignition_temp>
    <density>1.697</density>
    <vapour_density>5.32</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>2350</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Positive</mutagenicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50-  Pimephales promelas - 42 mg/l - 96 h  Lepomis macrochirus - 27 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna -  530 mg/l - 48 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Tetrachloromethane is a clear, colourless, highly volatile liquid with a sweet smell. It is non-flammable and doesn't mix with water. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="53">
        <standard>EN ISO 10301:1997</standard>
        <title>Determination of highly volatile halogenated hydrocarbons - Gas-chromatographic methods (ISO 10301:1997)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 40 and 50%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="54">
    <pollutant_name>Trichlorobenzenes (TCBs)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>TCBs are mainly used in chemical manufacture of dyes. They are also have a variety of uses as industrial solvents, insulating fluids, heat exchange fluids and degreasing agents.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The majority of releases occur through the manufacture, transport and use of the substances. Most releases are to the air, though some will be to land or water bodies.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to normal environmental concentrations of TCBs is unlikely to damage health. Exposure to high levels of this pollutant can lead to irritation of the skin, eyes and respiratory tract. They can also cause damage to the liver, kidneys and lungs. TCBs are very toxic to aquatic life and there is some evidence they accumulate through the food chain. As VOCs, they can be involved in reactions with other air pollutants that form harmful ground level ozone, which can cause damage to human health and plants.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>16</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>214</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.163</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>30</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>3.93</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>2.5% - 6.6%</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>105</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>571</autoignition_temp>
    <density>1.448</density>
    <toxicity>756</toxicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Gambusia affinis - 2.2 mg/l - 96 h.</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 1.45 mg/l - 48 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Trichlorobenzenes (TCBs) are colourless liquids with a pleasant smell. They are volatile and slightly soluble in water.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="54">
        <standard>EN ISO 15680:2003</standard>
        <title>Gas-chromatographic determination of a number of monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, naphthalene and several chlorinated compounds using purge-and-trap and thermal desorption (ISO 15680:2003)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="55">
    <pollutant_name>1,1,1-trichloroethane</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>1,1,1-Trichloroethane used to be widely applied as a solvent for cleaning metal parts and circuit boards, as a photoresist solvent in the electronics industry, as an aerosol propellant, as a cutting fluid additive, and as a solvent for inks, paints, adhesives and other coatings. Small amounts are released occasionally from domestic products such as spot cleaners, glues and aerosol sprays. Being an ozone depleter, its use has been banned since 2000 by the Montreal Protocol and only feedstock and laboratory uses are allowed.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>1,1,1-Trichloroethane is a man-made chemical with no natural sources. It is mostly released to the environment through evaporation during its use as a solvent but is also leached from contaminated landfill sites to the soil or groundwater.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to normal environmental concentrations is unlikely to damage health. High levels of 1,1,1-trichloroethane, such as following an accidental release or in an occupational setting may affect the brain, eye, heart, lung, central nervous system, kidneys and skin. Long-term exposure to less extreme levels might damage the liver. 1,1,1-trichloroethane (TCE) contributes to the depletion of the earth's ozone layer in the upper atmosphere. 1,1,1-Trichloroethane (TCE) can also contaminate water bodies and accumulate in aquatic life. Normal environmental levels are unlikely to damage local environment. However higher concentrations resulting from spillages can be toxic.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-30.1</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>74.1</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>122</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>1290</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>2.49</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>7.5% - 10.5%</flammable_limits>
    <autoignition_temp>500</autoignition_temp>
    <density>1.393</density>
    <vapour_density>4.63</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>9600</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Pimephales promelas - 53.00 mg/l - 96h, Cyprinus carpio - 7.7 mg/l - 14d, Pimephales promelas- 42.3 mg/l - 96h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 11.2 mg/l - 48 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>1,1,1-Trichloroethane (TCE) is a colourless, sweet smelling and highly volatile liquid.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="55">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title />
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="56">
    <pollutant_name>1,1,2,2-tetrachloroethane</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>1,1,2,2-tetrachloroethane is used mainly in the production of other chemicals. In the past it was used as an insecticide, fumigant and weed killer, and as a degreasing agent.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Releases to the environment are mainly through its manufacture and use. Most releases are to the atmosphere because it is so volatile. There are no natural sources.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure at normal background levels is unlikely to have an impact on human health. High levels of exposure can cause damage to the liver, kidneys and brain. 1,1,2,2- tetrachlorethane is toxic to aquatic life but does not appear to accumulate in fish or other organisms. In the atmosphere, as a VOC, it can be involved in the formation of harmful ground level ozone which can cause damage to human health and plants.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-43</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>142 </boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>4.62</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>2830</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>2.39</partition_coeff>
    <density>1.556</density>
    <vapour_density>5.8</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>200</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Pimephales promelas - 20 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50- Daphina magna -12-24 mg/l - 24 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>1,1,2,2-tetrachloroethane is a colourless, highly volatile liquid with a sweet smell.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="56">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title />
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="57">
    <pollutant_name>Trichloroethylene</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>The main uses of trichloroethylene are as a metal degreasing agent and as a solvent in paints, lubricants and paint strippers. In the past it was used for fumigating grain and as an anaesthetic. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>It is released mainly through its use as a solvent and disposing of products which contain it. There are no natural sources of trichloroethylene.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to normal environmental levels of trichloroethylene is not expected to cause any adverse heath effects. Exposure to high levels can cause headache, nausea, drowsiness and irregular heartbeat. It may also be carcinogenic. Trichloroethylene does not bio-accumulate in plants and animals and quickly evaporates to the air from water. It remains in soil for a long time. It is classed as a volatile organic compound (VOC) and can contribute to the formation of harmful ground level ozone which can cause damage to human health and plants. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-85</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>87.2</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>69</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>1280</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>2.61</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>8.0% - 10.5%</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>12.1</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>420</autoignition_temp>
    <density>1.474</density>
    <vapour_density>4.5</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>4920</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2A</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Positive</mutagenicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50  Pimephales promelas -  41 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna -18 mg/l - 48 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Trichloroethylene is a thick, colourless and volatile liquid with a sweet odour. It is classed as a VOC (Volatile Organic Compound).</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="57">
        <standard>EN ISO 15680:2003</standard>
        <title>Gas-chromatographic determination of a number of monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, naphthalene and several chlorinated compounds using purge-and-trap and thermal desorption (ISO 15680:2003)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="57">
        <standard>EN ISO 10301:1997</standard>
        <title>Determination of highly volatile halogenated hydrocarbons - Gas-chromatographic methods (ISO 10301:1997)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 40 and 50%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="58">
    <pollutant_name>Trichloromethane</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Chloroform is mostly used as a solvent and in the manufacture of chemicals such as pesticides. In the past it was used as an anaesthetic.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>It is released mainly through its use as a solvent and chemical intermediate. Most releases are to the air and releases to land or water will quickly evaporate into the air. There are no natural sources of chloroform.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to normal background levels is unlikely to have an effect on human health. Exposure to high levels can cause damage to the skin, liver, kidneys and nervous system. Most releases of chloroform will go into the atmosphere. Some may persist in water courses but it doesn't bio-accumulate in soils or sediments. As a VOC it can react in the air with other pollutants to form harmful ground level ozone which can cause damage to human health and plants.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-63</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>61.2 </boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>197</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>7950</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>1.97</partition_coeff>
    <density>1.5</density>
    <vapour_density>4.12</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>1194</toxicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Leuciscus idus - 162.00 mg/l - 48 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 79.00 mg/l - 24 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Trichloromethane is a colourless, highly volatile liquid with a distinctive smell. It is classed as a VOC (Volatile Organic Compound).</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="58">
        <standard>EN ISO 15680:2003</standard>
        <title>Gas-chromatographic determination of a number of monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, naphthalene and several chlorinated compounds using purge-and-trap and thermal desorption (ISO 15680:2003)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="58">
        <standard>EN ISO 10301:1997</standard>
        <title>Determination of highly volatile halogenated hydrocarbons - Gas-chromatographic methods (ISO 10301:1997)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 40 and 50%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="59">
    <pollutant_name>Toxaphene</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Toxaphene was previoulsy used as an insecticide. Its use has been banned in the EU under the Aarhus Protocol of the CLRTAP (Convention on Long-range Transboundary Air Pollution). </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Release of toxaphene will be through its use as an insecitcide,  from  hazardous waste sites and into the air by evaporation.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>There is no information on the effects of low level exposure, but when excessive amounts are inhaled or ingested, there could affect the lungs, the nervous system and the kidneys.</text>
	<text>Toxaphene degrades slowly in the environment and will bioaccumulate in fish and wildlife. It is volatile enough to be transported for long distances through the atmosphere. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>65-90</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>decomposes</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.00000669</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>3</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>5.9</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>135</flash_point>
    <density>1.66</density>
    <vapour_density>14.3</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>80-90</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B </carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Oncorhynchus mykiss - 0.0145 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Toxaphene can be found as a solid or a gas.  In its solid form, it is a yellow to amber in colour, appears waxy, and has a turpentine odour.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="59">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title />
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="60">
    <pollutant_name>Vinyl chloride</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Vinyl chloride is mainly used to manufacture PVC (polyvinylchloride) plastics which have a variety of uses.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Most releases of vinyl chloride are from the plastics industry. There are no natural sources of vinyl chloride.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to normal environmental concentrations of vinyl chloride is unlikely to damage health while exposure to high levels can cause damage to the blood, blood vessels, brain, eyes, kidneys, liver, lungs, immune system and reproductive system. Vinyl chloride can cause cancer. Vinyl chloride is mostly released to the atmosphere where it is easily broken down. In soils or water the compound is very mobile and may leach into groundwater. As a VOC it can react with other pollutants to form harmful ground level ozone which can cause damage to human health and plants.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Gas</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-153.7</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>  -13.9 </boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>2580</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>8800</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>1.62</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>3.6% - 33%</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>-78</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>472</autoignition_temp>
    <density>0.918</density>
    <vapour_density>2.15</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>500</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>1</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Positive</mutagenicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Esox lucius - 388 mg/l - 240 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Vinyl chloride is a gas at normal room temperature, with a faint sweet smell. It is highly flammable. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="60">
        <standard>EN ISO 15680:2003</standard>
        <title>Gas-chromatographic determination of a number of monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, naphthalene and several chlorinated compounds using purge-and-trap and thermal desorption (ISO 15680:2003)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="61">
    <pollutant_name>Anthracene</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Only small amounts of anthracene are manufactured for their use in dyes and sometimes pyrotechnics. It can also be found in creosote and tar paints.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Anthracene can be released to the environment when there is not sufficient oxygen to complete combustion. This can happen through car exhausts and wood fires. Anthracene is also released naturally from volcanoes, fires, and lightning strikes in small amounts.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Anthracene is a polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon (PAH) which takes a long time to break down in the environment and thus potentially bio-accumulates, mainly in water ecosystems. Anthracene is highly toxic to wildlife.</text>
	<text>Long-term exposure to this compound causes symptoms such as headaches, nausea, gut inflammation and irritation to the airways. If anthracene comes into contact with skin in high concentrations it can cause irritation and swelling.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point> 213-216</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>337.4</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.00000267</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.0434</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>4.45</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>121</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>540</autoignition_temp>
    <density>1.13</density>
    <vapour_density>6.15</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>17</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Negative</mutagenicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Lepomis macrochirus - 0.001 mg/l - 96 h </aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 0.095 mg/l - 48 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Anthracene is a colourless crystalline solid that is not soluble in water.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="61">
        <standard>ISO 11338-1 to -2:2003</standard>
        <title>Determination of gas and particle-phase polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons - Part 1: Sampling. Part 2: Sample preparation, clean-up and determination</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty reported is ± 25% for values  between 0.1 μg/m<sup>3</sup> to 1 μg/ m<sup>3</sup></uncertainty>   
      </provision>
      <provision id="61">
        <standard>EN ISO 17993:2003</standard>
        <title>Determination of 15 polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAH) in water by HPLC with fluorescence detection after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 17993:2002)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 2 and 5%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="62">
    <pollutant_name>Benzene</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Benzene is used in the production of dyes, detergents, coatings, plastics, fibres and pesticides. Benzene can also be found in petrol.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Benzene is mostly released from vehicle exhaust emmissions. Other significant releases are from its production and use in the manufacture of other chemicals, and from other types of fuel combustion. Benzene can be released naturally from fires and volcanoes, but these sources only contribute an insignificant amount.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Benzene is a known human carcinogen under conditions of chronic long-term exposure. At normal background levels it is not thought to damage human health. 

Extremely high levels of exposure to benzene, typically in accidental situations under operational settings can be fatal, whereas long-term exposure can affect blood-forming organs.</text>
	<text>Normal concentrations are not likely to cause damage or bioaccumulate in animals and plants. Airborne benzene can react with other pollutants to form ground-level ozone. Elevated levels of ozone can cause respiratory health problems and can lead to premature mortality. High levels of O3 also damage plants, reducing agricultural crop yields and decreasing forest growth. Water and soil contamination can be significant pathways for benzene exposure.  </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>5.5</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>80.1</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>94.8</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>1790</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>2.13</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>1.2% - 7.8%</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>-11</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>-497.8</autoignition_temp>
    <density>0.874</density>
    <vapour_density>2.8</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>3306</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>1</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Morone saxatilis - 5.8 to 11 mg/l 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Benzene is a colourless, highly flammable liquid with a distinctive odour. Benzene will evaporate easily.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="62">
        <standard>EN 13649:2001</standard>
        <title>Determination of the mass concentration of individual gaseous organic compounds - Activated carbon and solvent desorption method</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, at a 95% level of confidence, ranges between ±  4 and ± 11mg/m<sup>3</sup>, depending on sampling procedure, analyte and concentration</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="62">
        <standard>ISO 11423-1:1997</standard>
        <title>Determination of benzene and some derivatives - Part 1: Head-space gas chromatograhic method</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 1 and 50%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="62">
        <standard>ISO 11423-2:1997</standard>
        <title>Determination of benzene and some derivatives - Part 2: Method using extraction and gas chromatography</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 22 and 47%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="62">
        <standard>EN ISO 15680:2003</standard>
        <title>Gas-chromatographic determination of a number of monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, naphthalene and several chlorinated compounds using purge-and-trap and thermal desorption (ISO 15680:2003)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="63">
    <pollutant_name>Brominated diphenylethers (PBDE)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>PBDEs are mainly used as fire retardants in plastics and foams.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Most releases to the environment are through their manufacture and when the materials they are added to are disposed of in landfill or incinerators. They are also released slowly from the products that contain them.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to high levels of PBDEs may affect the brain and liver. The effects of low levels of exposure on human health are unknown. PBDEs are toxic to aquatic animals and may cause long term effects on the aquatic environment. PBDEs are highly persistent and bioaccumulative.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-7- -3</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>Decomposes</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.0000022 - 0.0000055</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.0133</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>6.64 - 6.97</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>Not combustible</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>Not combustible</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>Not combustible</autoignition_temp>
    <density>2.25 - 2.28</density>
    <toxicity>2640</toxicity>
    <description>Brominated diphenyl ethers (PBDE) are thick liquids or solids which are usually non-flammable and non-volatile. They are usually insoluble in water.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="63">
        <standard>ISO 22032:2006</standard>
        <title>Determination of selected polybrominated diphenyl ethers in sediment and sewage sludge - Method using extraction and gas chromatography/mass spectrometry</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 50%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="64">
    <pollutant_name>Nonylphenol and Nonylphenol ethoxylates (NP/NPEs)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Nonylphenols are used to produce nonylphenol ethoxylates. They are also used in a large number of laboratory processes. They are also added to a number of commercial products including paints, adhesives and pesticides.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Nonylphenols will be released during the manufacturing processes that use them. Nonylphenols are also released when nonylphenol ethoxylates break down in the environment. There are no natural sources.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Nonylphenols are thought to be very toxic to wildlife and can be very persistent in the environment. Thus, it is possible that the presence of these chemicals will have a long-term effect at a global or local scale. Nonylphenols are accumulated and concentrated by aquatic organisms and birds.</text>
	<text>These chemicals are endocrine disruptors, which can contribute to various health problems in humans although full information on the toxicological effect of nonylphenols is not complete. To date, the available information indicates that normal background levels are not thought to damage human health. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid/Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-10</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>293-297 </boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.0000236</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>6.35</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>5.71</partition_coeff>
    <dissocation_const>10.25</dissocation_const>
    <flammable_limits>0.01</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>141</flash_point>
    <density>0.95</density>
    <vapour_density>7.59</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>1600</toxicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Salmo gairdneri - 0.56-0.92 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Nonylphenols are thick liquids which are colourless to pale yellow. They are inert and insoluble in water. 4-nonylphenol is provided as an example.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="64">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title />
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="65">
    <pollutant_name>Ethyl benzene</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Ethyl benzene is used in the production of chemicals and other products including rubber and plastics.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The main release is from the chemical and petroleum industries and other processes of combustion. Ethyl benzene can also be found in cigarette smoke.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Normal environmental concentrations of ethylbenzene and exposure to high concentrations during limited periods of time are not thought to damage human health significantly. However, long-term exposure at high concentrations is considered toxic. </text>
	<text>Normal concentrations are not likely to cause damage or bioaccumulation in animals or plants. Airborne ethyl benzene can however easily react with other pollutants to form harmful ground level ozone which can cause damage to human health and plants. Ethyl benzene is not thought to affect the environment on a global scale.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-95</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>136.1</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>9.6</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>169</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>3.15</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>1% - 6.7%</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>12.8</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>432</autoignition_temp>
    <density>0.867</density>
    <vapour_density>3.66</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>3500</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B </carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Cyprinodon variegatus - 275 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Ethyl benzene is a sweet-smelling, colourless, liquid that will evaporate easily.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="65">
        <standard>EN ISO 15680:2003</standard>
        <title>Gas-chromatographic determination of a number of monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, naphthalene and several chlorinated compounds using purge-and-trap and thermal desorption (ISO 15680:2003)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="66">
    <pollutant_name>Ethylene oxide</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Ethylene oxide is used in the chemical industry to produce products such as antifreeze, cosmetics and pharmaceuticals due to its highly reactive properties.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The largest releases of ethylene oxide are from industries that are using the chemical. Smaller amounts can be released from volcanoes and living organisms.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Ethylene oxide is a carcinogen, although exposure at background levels is unlikely to damage human health. Low levels over a long period of time can lead to irritation of the skin and eyes. Exposure to high concentrations of ethylene oxide may cause damage to water ecosystems but it does not bio-accumulate. This pollutant is not thought to affect the environment on a global scale.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Gas</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-111.7</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>10.6</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>1310</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>Miscible</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>-0.3</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>3.0% - 100%</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>-29</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>429</autoignition_temp>
    <density>0.882</density>
    <vapour_density>1.49</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>330</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>1</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Positive</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Pimephales promelas - 84000 ug/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Ethylene oxide is colourless gas with no odour. It is very reactive and highly flammable.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="66">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title />
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="67">
    <pollutant_name>Isoproturon</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Isoproturon is a pre and post-emergence herbicide which works by inhibiting photosynthesis.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Isoproturon is released to the environment through its use as a pesticide. There are no natural sources of isoproturon.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Background exposure levels to isoproturon are not thought to damage human health. </text>
	<text>Although no significant global impacts are considered to be likely, isoproturon is considered to be dangerous to the environment and very toxic to aquatic organisms. Isoproturon can be persistent in water bodies but it is broken down easily by microorganisms in soils.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>158</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>353.2</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.000000018</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>65</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>2.5</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>167.4</flash_point>
    <density>1.05</density>
    <toxicity>1826-2417</toxicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Oncorhynchus mykiss - 37 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Isoproturon is in the form of colourless crystals which are highly soluble in water and organic solvents.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="67">
        <standard>No International standard</standard>
        <title />
        <target />
        <uncertainty />
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="68">
    <pollutant_name>Naphthalene</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Naphthalene is used in mothballs, insecticides, and the manufacture of dyes.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The largest releases of naphthalene are from the burning of fossil fuels. Naphthalene can also be released when used in the chemical industry and where products containing the chemical have been disposed of.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Naphthalene is a carcinogen, although exposure at background levels is unlikely to damage human health. Inhalation of elevated levels can cause harmful effects to health such as headaches, nausea, and in some cases coma. Exposure to high concentrations of naphthalene is toxic to wildlife and aquatic organisms, although it breaks down easily in the environment.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>80.2</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>217.9</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.085</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>31</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>3.3</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>0.9% - 5.9%</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>79</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>526</autoignition_temp>
    <density>1.162</density>
    <vapour_density>4.42</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>490</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>2B </carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Negative</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Oncorhynchus gorbuscha - 1.4 mg/l -  96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Napthalene is a white to brown flammable solid with a strong odour and evaporates easily.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="68">
        <standard>ISO 11338-1 to -2:2003</standard>
        <title>Determination of gas and particle-phase polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons - Part 1: Sampling. Part 2: Sample preparation, clean-up and determination. </title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty  is ± 25% for values  between 0.1 μg/m<sup>3</sup> and 1 μg/m<sup>3</sup></uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="68">
        <standard>EN ISO 15680:2003</standard>
        <title>Gas-chromatographic determination of a number of monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, naphthalene and several chlorinated compounds using purge-and-trap and thermal desorption (ISO 15680:2003)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="68">
        <standard>EN ISO 17993:2003</standard>
        <title>Determination of 15 polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAH) in water by HPLC with fluorescence detection after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 17993:2002)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 2 and 5% </uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="69">
    <pollutant_name>Organotin compounds (as total Sn)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Di-substituted organotins are used as strengthening agents in plastics, where tri-substituted organotins are used as marine pesticides and preservatives.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Releases of organotin compounds will be from their use in industry, although small amounts are released via the Earth's crust.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>If exposed to normal background levels of organotin compounds, no health problems are expected. Long-term exposure in occupational settings may cause irritation and breathing difficulties. The exact effects on health are dependent on the compound in question. Organotins are of greatest concern in marine environments as they can accumulate in fish and concentrate through the food chain. There are not known global impacts of organotin compounds on the environment.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-43</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>275.3</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.0086 </vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>Insoluble</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>0.97</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>107.8</flash_point>
    <vapour_density>10.5</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>219</toxicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Leuciscus idus 0.6 mg/l - 48hr</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Cyprinodon bariegatus &gt;4.8 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Organotins are compounds with a tin molecule bound to an organic compound. Therefore the properties will be chemical specific. Dibutyltin chloride is provided as an example</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="69">
        <standard>EN ISO 17353:2005</standard>
        <title>Determination of selected organotin compounds - Gas chromatographic method (ISO 17353:2004)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 16 and 39%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="70">
    <pollutant_name>Di-(2-ethyl hexyl) phthalate (DEHP)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>DEHP is used in the production of PVC to make it more flexible.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>DEHP has the potential to leach or evaporate from the products that contain it, and also when products have been disposed of to landfill.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>The effects of DEHP to human health are not clearly known. However, background levels of DEHP are not thought to cause any adverse health effects. DEHP is highly persistent in the environment and bio-accumulative. DEHP presents effects on the endocrine system as a disruptor and therefore poses long-term problems to wildlife.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-55</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>416.4</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.000000384</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.27</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>7.6</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>222.3</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>390</autoignition_temp>
    <density>0.985</density>
    <toxicity>30000</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Negative</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Pimephales promelas - &gt; 0.67 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - &gt; 0.16 mg/l - 48 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>DEHP is a pale yellow oily liquid with a slight odour and does not evaporate easily. DEHP is in a group of chemicals named phthalates.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="70">
        <standard>EN ISO 18856:2005</standard>
        <title>Determination of selected phthalates using gas chromatography/mass spectrometry (ISO 18856:2004)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 18 and 86%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="71">
    <pollutant_name>Phenols (as total C)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Phenols are used for the manufacturer of chemicals and resins. Phenols occur naturally in the environment and are also man made.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Phenols are released to the environment as a waste product from industrial practices and their use as pesticides.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>At normal environmental concentrations, phenols are unlikely to damage wildlife, plants or human health. Long-term exposure to high concentrations of phenol, normally in occupational settings, may have adverse effects. Man-made phenols have a low volatility and therefore will persist in the environment. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>42.5-43</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>182</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.4</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>82800</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>1.46</partition_coeff>
    <dissocation_const>9.99</dissocation_const>
    <ph>6</ph>
    <flammable_limits>1.7% - 8.6%</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>79</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>715</autoignition_temp>
    <density>1.071</density>
    <vapour_density>3.24</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>530</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Pimephales promelas - 41-36 mg/l</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Phenol in its pure form are colourless to white crystals with an antiseptic odour. Technical grade can be pink crystals or even a liquid. Phenol with dissolve relatively well in water.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="71">
        <standard>EN ISO 14402:1999</standard>
        <title>Determination of phenol index by flow analysis (FIA and CFA) (ISO 14402:1999)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
       <uncertainty> The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 81%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="72">
    <pollutant_name>Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>PAHs have only been used for research purposes are are not intentionally manufactured.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The majority of PAHs are released by combustion processes, evaporation from materials treated with creosote, mineral oils, pitch. Also from wash-off from bitumen roads. They can also be released naturally from forest fires.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons are a large group of chemicals which contribute to different harmful effects in the environment and to human health. Exposures to high concentrations of PAHs may affect the eyes, liver, skin, and immune system. Some PAHs also may cause genetic damage and cancer.  </text>
	<text>PAHs have an ability to travel long distances in the atmosphere when attached to soot particles. Therefore they can contribute to adverse effects occurring to wildlife in places far from the point of release.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>177</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>312</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.00000000549</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>Slightly soluble</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>5.97</partition_coeff>
    <density>1.351</density>
    <vapour_density>8.7</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>15</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>1 - [Benzo[a]pyrene]
Group 3 - [Benzo[e]pyrene]
Group 3 - [Benzo[b]chrysene]</carcinogenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Daphnia pulex - 0.05 mg/l 96hr</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Pure PAHs are found as a crystalline solid. In the environment they will be absorbed onto particles of soot.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="72">
        <standard>ISO 11338-1 to -2:2003</standard>
        <title>Determination of gas and particle-phase polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons - Part 1: Sampling. Part 2: Sample preparation, clean-up and determination. </title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty> Typical  uncertainty is +/- 25% for values  between 0.1 μg/m<sup>3</sup>  and 1 μg/m<sup>3</sup>   </uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="72">
        <standard>EN ISO 17993:2003</standard>
        <title>Determination of 15 polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAH) in water by HPLC with fluorescence detection after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 17993:2002)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 2 and 5%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="72">
        <standard>ISO 7981-1:2005</standard>
        <title>Determination of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAH) - Part 1: Determination of six PAH by high-performance thin-layer chromatography with fluorescence detection after liquid-liquid extraction</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 16 and 24%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="72">
        <standard>ISO 7981-2:2005</standard>
        <title>Determination of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAH) - Part 2: Determination of six PAH by high-performance liquid chromatography with fluorescence detection after liquid-liquid extraction</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 14.80%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="73">
    <pollutant_name>Toluene</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Toluene is used as a solvent and is often blended into petrol. It is also used in paints, thinners, adhesives and some printing processes.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Toluene is released during the combustion of fuels and from evaporation of toluene-containing products such as paint and paint thinners, adhesives and nail polish as they are used and disposed of. </text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Background exposure levels of toluene are not thought to cause adverse health effects. However, after a large exposure to toluene possible impacts include harm to the eyes, throat, brain and the unborn child. </text>
	<text>Toluene evaporates quickly and will not persist in soil and surface water. Toluene can contribute to the formation of harmful ground-level ozone which can cause damage to human health and plants.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-95</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>111</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>21.3</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.0016</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>2.73</partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>1.1% -  7.1%</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>4</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>480</autoignition_temp>
    <density>0.864</density>
    <vapour_density>3.1</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>5000</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Pimephales promelas - 34.27 mg/l 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Toluene is a colourless, highly flammable liquid which is immiscible in water. It is a member of the BTEX group of pollutants.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="73">
        <standard>EN ISO 15680:2003</standard>
        <title>Gas-chromatographic determination of a number of monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, naphthalene and several chlorinated compounds using purge-and-trap and thermal desorption (ISO 15680:2003)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>      
		</provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="74">
    <pollutant_name>Tributyltin and compounds</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>The major use of TBTs is as a marine anti-fouling agent. They are also used as a fungicide in preservatives for wood.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The major source of TBTs is through the gradual release from products treated with the pesticide. There are no natural sources of TBTs.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Background exposure levels to TBTs are not thought to damage human health. However, there is concern that exposure to TBTs can interfere with animal hormones and that they are endocrine disruptors. </text>
	<text>TBTs accumulate in both fish and other aquatic life.  Due to their low solubility in water, they are not particularly mobile. TBTs will bind to soils and persist in the environment for a long period of time, but they are not thought to cause a global issue.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-45</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>180</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>&lt;1 </vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>4</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>3.84</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>&gt;100</flash_point>
    <density>1.17</density>
    <toxicity>194</toxicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Pimephales promelas -  2.4-3 mg/l</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description> Man-made organic compounds which contain tin. They are colourless to yellow liquids with a foul odour. Data for Tributyltin oxide is provided as an example.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="74">
        <standard>EN ISO 17353:2005</standard>
        <title>Determination of selected organotin compounds - Gas chromatographic method (ISO 17353:2004) </title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 16 and 39%</uncertainty>  
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="75">
    <pollutant_name>Triphenyltin and compounds</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>The major use of triphenyltin compounds is as a pesticide and/or biocide in marine anti-fouling paints. They are also used as a fungicide in preservatives for wood.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Released primarily from their use in marine antifouling paints, as fungicides in wood preservatives, crop protection and potentially from their manufacture, transport and storage. There are no natural sources of triphenyltin compounds.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Background exposure levels to triphenyltin compounds are not thought to damage human health. </text>
	<text>Triphenyltin compounds can be toxic to wildlife and bioaccumulate in the tissues of living organisms. As triphenyltin compounds are insoluble, they tend to bind to soil and persist for long periods of time.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>26-28</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>162-168</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.00000159</vapour_pressure>
    <toxicity>491</toxicity>
    <description>Triphenyltin compounds are generally colourless/white solids or liquids that are practically insoluble.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="75">
        <standard>EN ISO 17353:2005</standard>
        <title>Determination of selected organotin compounds - Gas chromatographic method (ISO 17353:2004) </title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 16 and 39%</uncertainty>  
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="76">
    <pollutant_name>Total organic carbon (TOC) (as total C or COD/3)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Total Organic Carbon (TOC) has no use as such. It is a term which is used in the measurement and classification of water quality.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Any man-made or natural process that will result in the release of TOC to water. For example, sewage treatment works and leachate from landfills.
	</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Total Organic Carbon is a parameter often used as a non-specific indicator of water quality. It includes many different chemicals. Therefore, it is not possible to identify the health concerns as they differ depending on the particular chemicals involved in each case.</text>
	<text>High levels of TOC in a natural water body will undermine the ecosystem's operation since it fosters the growth of anaerobic bacteria due to a low oxygen concentration. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <description>Total organic carbon (TOC)  describes any organic (carbon-containing) compound that will dissolve in water.  TOC represents a very large number of different compounds. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="76">
        <standard>EN 1484:1997</standard>
        <title>Guidelines for the determination of total organic carbon (TOC) and dissolved organic carbon (DOC)</title>
        <target>Water analysis</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 4.5%</uncertainty>  
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="77">
    <pollutant_name>Trifluralin</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Trifluralin is used as a herbicide to control weed growth amongst crops.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The release of trifluralin into the environment is from its use as a pesticide. There are no natural sources of trifluralin.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Background exposure levels to trifluralin compounds are not thought to damage human health. Trifluralin is considered to be harmful to wildlife, with some types of aquatic organisms being more sensitive to the effects of trifluralin. Trifluralin binds to soil, but is broken down by plants and animals. In the atmosphere or surface waters, Trifluralin is broken down quickly by sunlight.</text>
	<text>It is not considered likely that trifluralin pollution has any effects on the global environment.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>48.5-49</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>139-140</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.0000458</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.184</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>4.83</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>153</flash_point>
    <density>1.32</density>
    <toxicity>&gt;5000 </toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Positive</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Oncorhynchus Mykiss - 0.088 mg/l</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Algae selenastrum capricornutum - 12.2 mg/l</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Pure trifluralin is in the form of orange crystals with no odour, it also evaporates easily. When heated, toxic and corrosive fumes are formed.</description>
    <iso_provisions />
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="78">
    <pollutant_name>Xylenes</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Xylene is used in the manufacturing of chemicals, plastics, in solvents and in paints.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Xylenes are both naturally occuring chemicals and are manufactured by man. The petroleum and chemical industries release the greater proportion of xylene through combustion processes. They are also released when natural materials burn.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to xylenes at normal background levels is unlikely to lead to adverse effects occurring for human health. Large exposures of xylenes may cause adverse health effects to the brain, digestive system, hearty, ears, eyes, liver, lungs, skin and throat.  </text>
	<text>Xylenes can be toxic to wildlife and they are also volatile organic compounds (VOCs) that can contribute to harmful ground-level ozone which can cause damage to human health and plants.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-54</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>137-143</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>4.88</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>130</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>3.12-3.20 </partition_coeff>
    <flammable_limits>1% - 7%</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>17 - 25</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>464</autoignition_temp>
    <density>0.86</density>
    <vapour_density>3.7</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>5400</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Negative</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Oncorhynchus mykiss - 8.2 mg/l</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphina magna - 3.82 mg/l</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Xylenes are colourless, sweet-smelling flammable liquids that are a member of the BTEX group of pollutants.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="78">
        <standard>EN ISO 15680:2003</standard>
        <title>Gas-chromatographic determination of a number of monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, naphthalene and several chlorinated compounds using purge-and-trap and thermal desorption (ISO 15680:2003) </title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="79">
    <pollutant_name>Chlorides (as total Cl)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Common salt or rock salt is used for de-icing roads, in water softeners and as a flavour enhancer in food. There are many other uses for the many different types of chloride salt.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The release of chlorides is mainly due to their use in industry. Other releases include their use to de-ice roads, agricultural run-off, landfill leachate and coal-ash waste. Chlorides are frequently found in nature, for example in sea-water.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Background levels of chlorides in the environment are unlikely to cause damage to health and releases of chlorides are unlikely to cause adverse effects long distances away from the point of emission. Changes in the concentration of chlorides may cause unbalances in the impacted ecosystems, especially in water bodies. </text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>770</melt_freeze_point>
    <flammable_limits>non flammable</flammable_limits>
    <toxicity>2600</toxicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Leuciscus idus - 2300 mg/l - 48 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Chlorine is a reactive gas which is generally found in the environment as chloride salts which are usually highly soluble in water. Potassium chloride is provided as an example.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="79">
        <standard>EN ISO 10304-1:2009</standard>
        <title>Determination of dissolved fluoride, chloride, nitrite, orthophosphate, bromide, nitrate and sulfate ions, using liquid chromatography of ions - Part 1: Method for water with low contamination (ISO 10304-1:2007) </title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 0.5 and 2.5%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="79">
        <standard>EN ISO 10304-2:1997</standard>
        <title>Determination of dissolved anions by liquid chromatography of ions - Part 2: Determination of bromide, chloride, nitrate, nitrite, orthophosphate and sulfate in waste water</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty >The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 0.5 and 2.5%</uncertainty >
      </provision>
      <provision id="79">
        <standard>EN ISO 10304-4:1999</standard>
        <title>Determination of dissolved anions by liquid chromatography of ions - Part 4: Determination of chlorate, chloride and chlorite in water with low contamination (ISO 10304-4:1997)</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 5.4%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="79">
        <standard>EN ISO 15682:2001</standard>
        <title>Determination of chloride by flow analysis (CFA and FIA) and photometric or potentiometric detection (ISO 15682:2000) </title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 2.8%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="80">
    <pollutant_name>Chlorine and inorganic compounds (as HCl)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Colourless, chemically reactive gas with a strong odour. Hydrochloric acid (HCl) will be formed in contact with water.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The main source of release will be from coal-burning power stations. Smaller amounts can be released from waste incinerators, especially where plastic PVC has been incinerated.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Normal background exposure to hydrogen chloride will not harm human health.</text>
	<text>Harm to wildlife is unlikely to result from normal releases from industrial facilities but accidental emissions of large discharges to water can significantly affect water ecosystems.
Hydrogen chloride is highly corrosive and attacks many metals and limestone, resulting in the corrosion of buildings and other cultural monuments. 
</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Gas</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-101</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>- 34.1</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>5830</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>6300</water_solubility>
    <density>2.898</density>
    <vapour_density>2.48</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>147</toxicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Daphnia Pulex - 0.49mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Colourless, chemically reactive gas with a strong odour. Hydrochloric acid (HCl) will be formed in contact with water.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="80">
        <standard>EN 1911-1 TO -3:1998</standard>
        <title>Manual method of determination of HCl - Part 1: Sampling of gases. Part 2: Gaseous compounds absorption. Part 3: Absorption solutions analysis and calculation</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, at a 95% level of confidence, ranges  between  +/- 0.15 mg/m<sup>3</sup>  for values  about  0.1 mg/m<sup>3</sup>  and +/-12 mg/m<sup>3</sup>  for values about 215 mg/m<sup>3</sup></uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="81">
    <pollutant_name>Asbestos</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Due to the insulating properties of asbestos, it has been used for pipe coverings, insulation in buildings, cement and fireproof clothing.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Asbestos may be released to the environment by the dumping of asbestos wastes and maintenance work on buildings containing asbestos. A major source is from the demolition of old structures.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Scientific evidence suggests that asbestos is a carcinogen and a cause of various bronchial conditions: Asbestos remains in the lungs once inhaled.</text>
	<text>Asbestos does not appear to bind to the solids normally found in natural water systems. However, asbestos is resistant to burning, chemical exposure or degradation and it is very persistent in the environment. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>1500 - 1200</melt_freeze_point>
    <water_solubility>insoluble</water_solubility>
    <flammable_limits>non flammable</flammable_limits>
    <density>0.24 - 0.45</density>
    <carcinogenicity>1</carcinogenicity>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 825 mg/l - 48 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Asbestos is the name given to a group of heat-resistant mineral fibres which naturally occur in the environment.  </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="81">
        <standard>ISO 10397:1993</standard>
        <title>Determination of asbestos plant emissions; method by fibre count measurement</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>-</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="82">
    <pollutant_name>Cyanides (as total CN)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Cyanide compounds are used in a variety of industrial processes including chemical and plastic production, rubber and explosives and as pesticides. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Releases of cyanide in the environment are from vehicle exhausts, during industrial processes, waste incineration and their use as pesticides. Small quantities are released naturally from some foods and plants.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to damaging levels of cyanide does not occur at typical concentrations found in the environment but only by industrial usage and accidental spillages. In such conditions, cyanides are toxic by ingestion, skin contact and by inhalation.</text>
	<text>There are not thought to be any global effects to the environment as cyanides are generally not persistent when released to water and soil, and are not likely to accumulate in aquatic life. They can rapidly evaporate from water and soils and can be broken down by microbes.Cyanides generally do not bind to soils and thus may leach to groundwater. </text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>563</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>1496</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>1 mm Hg @ 817 deg C</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>44</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>-1.69</partition_coeff>
    <dissocation_const>9.2</dissocation_const>
    <ph>11.7</ph>
    <density>1.595</density>
    <toxicity>15</toxicity>
    <mutagenicity>Negitive</mutagenicity>
    <description>Cyanides are usually found in combination with hydrogen, sodium and potassium. Hydrogen cyanide is a colourless gas with an almond odour, where sodium and potassium cyanide are white solids with a similar odour.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="82">
        <standard>EN ISO 14403:2002</standard>
        <title>Determination of total cyanide and free cyanide by continuous flow analysis (ISO 14403:2002</title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 28.1%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="83">
    <pollutant_name>Fluorides (as total F)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Hydrogen fluoride is used in industry for the production of fluorocarbons and aluminium fluoride. Fluorides are used in the manufacture of glass, brick and ceramics. Toothpaste and drinking water often have fluorides added to prevent tooth decay.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Most fluorides are released from industrial activities, such as  coal combustion and process waters and waste from various industrial processes, including metal production, phosphate ore processing, phosphate fertiliser production, glass, brick and ceramic manufacturing. Fluorides are also released naturally through the earth's crust and sea spray.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Fluorides are found throughout the environment at various concentration levels since they are a major constituent of many materials (mineral, rocks). Due to this natural presence, emissions of fluorides do not have a global impact on the environment. However, local emissions leading to abnormal levels of fluorides may have environmental and health consequences. Many fluorine compounds are toxic and can harm wildlife due to bioaccumulation. Fluorides accumulate in the bone tissue of terrestrial vertebrates, depending on factors such as diet and the proximity of fluoride emission sources. They also accumulate in aquatic organisms directly from the water or to a lesser extent via food. </text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <description>Fluorine is a reactive gas that is normally found in combination with either metals or hydrogen to form a salt called a fluoride. Fluorides are usually white solids which are readily soluble in water. Sodium Fluoride is used as an example. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="83">
        <standard>EN ISO 10304-1:1995</standard>
        <title>Determination of dissolved fluoride, chloride, nitrite, orthophosphate, bromide, nitrate and sulfate ions, using liquid chromatography of ions - Part 1: Method for water with low contamination (ISO 10304-1:2007) </title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
       <uncertainty>-</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="84">
    <pollutant_name>Fluorine and inorganic compounds (as HF)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>HF is used in chemical synthesis and the refining of uranium as nuclear fuel, metal processing and glass etching.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release><text>The major release of hydrogen fluoride is through industrial processes (particularly from the chemical and metal processing industries) and from coal combustion. Fluorides are released from their use in pesticides and as additives in drinking water. They are also released naturally from the earth's crust and sea spray.</text></main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Normal background levels will not harm human health. </text>
	<text>Concentrations found naturally do not affect wildlife or vegetation, however, higher levels can be toxic and accumulate in the environment and concentrate through the food chain.
Long-term exposure has been known to cause bone problems.

The fluoride ion highly toxic since it interferes in the assimilation processes of some key nutrients like calcium or magnesium. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Gas</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-219.61</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>-188.13</boiling_point>
    <water_solubility>1.69</water_solubility>
    <density>1.5127</density>
    <vapour_density>1.695</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>93</toxicity>
    <description>Fluorine is a reactive, colourless gas which will rapidly dissolve in water to form a very corrosive liquid, known as hydrofluoric acid (HF). </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="84">
        <standard>ISO 15713:2006</standard>
        <title>Sampling and determination of gaseous fluoride content</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>-</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="85">
    <pollutant_name>Hydrogen cyanide (HCN)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>The primary use of hydrogen cyanide is for the manufacture of organic chemicals used in the synthetic fibres and plastic industries. It is also used in metal processing and as an industrial fumigant. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>The main release of hydrogen cyanide is through its use in industrial applications. Hydrogen cyanide occurs naturally in small amounts from some plants.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Hydrogen cyanide is generally not persistent when released to water and soil, and it does not accumulate in water ecosystems. It can rapidly evaporate from water and soils and can be broken down by microbes. It generally does not bind to soils and may leach to groundwater. It is however toxic to fish and other forms of aquatic life. </text>
	<text>At high concentrations, hydrogen cyanide is also toxic by ingestion and skin contact. It deeply interferes in respiration and as a result the brain and the cardiovascular system are affected.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Liquid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>-13</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>26</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>742</vapour_pressure>
    <partition_coeff>-0.25</partition_coeff>
    <ph>7.4</ph>
    <flammable_limits>5.6% - 40%</flammable_limits>
    <flash_point>-18</flash_point>
    <autoignition_temp>538</autoignition_temp>
    <density>0.687</density>
    <vapour_density>0.94</vapour_density>
    <toxicity>136</toxicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <description>Hydrogen cyanide is a colourless gas with an almond-like odour which is very flammable and potentially explosive in contact with air.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="85">
        <standard>EN ISO 14403:2002</standard>
        <title>Determination of total cyanide and free cyanide by continuous flow analysis (ISO 14403:2002) </title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility is 7.9%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="86">
    <pollutant_name>Particulate matter (PM10)</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Many industrial and combustion processes use or generate substances in a particulate form.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Particulate matter is mostly produced by combustion of fuels, waste incineration, building and construction, quarrying activities and other industrial processes.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>In terms of potential to harm human health, particulate matter is one of the most important pollutants as it penetrates into sensitive regions of the respiratory system, exacerbating respiratory illnesses such as asthma and contributing to increased prevalence and incidence of other cardiovascular diseases and premature death. Smaller sizes of particulate matter (e.g. PM<sub>2.5</sub>) are considered particularly harmful due to their greater ability to penetrate deeply into lungs.</text>
	<text>At a global scale, particulate matter contributes to climate change through its ability to alter the radiative forcing of the atmosphere. </text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <description>Particulate matter is a term used to describe fine particles of carbon, metals and inorganic salts suspended in a gas or liquid. PM10 is the term used to describe particulate matter smaller than 10 microns in size. The chemical composition of these fine particles depends on their source; when containing mineral oxides particular matter is light-absorbing.</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="86">
        <standard>ISO 23210:2009</standard>
        <title>Determination of low PM10/PM2,5 mass concentration in flue gas.  Measurement at low concentrations by use of impactors</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty, at a 95% level of confidence, ranges between  +/- 0.6 mg/m<sup>3</sup> for values about  5.6 mg/m<sup>3</sup> and +/- 4.8 mg/m<sup>3</sup> at values about 35 mg/m<sup>3</sup> </uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="86">
        <standard>EN 13284-1:2001</standard>
        <title>Determination of low range mass concentration of dust. Manual gravimetric method</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty is about +/- 1.8 mg/m<sup>3</sup> at levels of about 2.5 mg/m<sup>3</sup></uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="86">
        <standard>EN 13284-2:2004</standard>
        <title>Determination of low range mass concentration of dust - Part 2: Automated measuring systems</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
      <provision id="86">
        <standard>ISO 9096:2003</standard>
        <title>Manual determination of mass concentration of particulate matter</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>*</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="87">
    <pollutant_name>Octylphenols and Octylphenol ethoxylates</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Octylphenols are found in many products such as rubber, detergents, non-ionic surfactants, plasticizers, antioxidants, pesticides, bactericides, dyestuffs and adhesives. The main areas of use are as an intermediate in the production of phenol/formaldehyde resins and in the manufacture of octylphenol ethoxylates.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Octylphenols and Octylphenol ethoxylates are released to the environment  largely through their use in cleaning products and other products that contain them. They are not produced naturally.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to octylphenols at normal background levels is unlikely to have adverse effects on human health.</text>
	<text>In the environment octylphenols and octylphenol exthoxylates are toxic to wildlife, particularly aquatic organisms. They bio-accumulate and there are concerns that they are hormone disrupting substances, mimicking the behaviour of animal hormones. They can be very persistent in the environment and can be transported far from the point of original release posing a threat to wildlife.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>44-45</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>280 - 302 </boiling_point>
    <flash_point>&gt;110</flash_point>
    <density>0.89</density>
    <description>Octyl phenols and octyl phenol ethoxylates are usually white crystalline solids, they are generally unreactive and have a low solubility in water. Considering the low vapour pressure of octylphenol and its tendency to adsorb to soils and sediments, it can be expected that atmospheric concentrations will be low.  4-Octylphenol is provided as an example.</description>
    <iso_provisions />
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="88">
    <pollutant_name>Fluoranthene</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Fluoranthene is used in the manufacture of flourescent dyes, pharmaceuticals and agrochemicals.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Fluoranthene can be released to atmosphere from the incomplete combustion of wood, coal, oil, propane, gasoline, and diesel fuels, and is also found in cigarette smoke. It can also be released naturally from forest fires.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Fluoranthene is part of the group of PAHs and there is scientific evidence that it is a carcinogenic. With regard to its properties to persist in the environment it behaves similarly to other PAHs.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>105 - 110</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>384</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.00000922</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.26</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>5.16</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>168.4</flash_point>
    <density>1.248</density>
    <toxicity>2000</toxicity>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Oncorhynchus mykiss - 0.0077 mg/l - 96 h</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <aquatic_tox_ec50>EC50 - Daphnia magna - 0.78 mg/l - 20 h</aquatic_tox_ec50>
    <description>Fluoranthene is a polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon (PAH) that appears as a yellow to green needle-like solid which is practically insoluble in water. </description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="88">
        <standard>ISO 11338-1 to -2:2003</standard>
        <title>Determination of gas and particle-phase polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons - Part 1: Sampling. Part 2: Sample preparation, clean-up and determination.</title>
        <target>Stationary source emissions</target>
        <uncertainty>Typical uncertainty is +/- 25% for values  between 0.1 μg/m<sup>3</sup> to 1 μg/m<sup>3</sup>  </uncertainty> 
      </provision>
      <provision id="88">
        <standard>EN ISO 17993:2003</standard>
        <title>Determination of 15 polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAH) in water by HPLC with fluorescence detection after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 17993:2002) </title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 2 and 5%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="89">
    <pollutant_name>Isodrin</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Isodrin was once used as an insecticide for agricultural control of disease-spreading insects. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Where isodrin is still used, the main release to the environment will be through its use as a pesticide. There are no natural sources of isodrin.</text>	
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Isodrin does not degrade easily and can persist in the environment for many years. It is highly toxic to wildlife and long-term damage to sensitive species is likely. This substance is rather stable and this leads to a long-distance transportation and persistency in the environment. Isodrin is fat soluble and it can bioaccumulate through the food chain. </text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>240-242</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>384.9</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.000044</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.014</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>6.75</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>186.1</flash_point>
    <density>1.73</density>
    <toxicity>7</toxicity>
    <persistence>Inadequate evidence</persistence>
    <description>A white crystalline solid with a chemical-like odour.</description>
    <iso_provisions />
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="90">
    <pollutant_name>Hexabromobiphenyl</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Hexabromobiphenyl is used as a fire retardant. It is mostly added to plastics which are used in electrical appliances.</main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>Releases of hexabromobiphenyl result from its use as a fire retardant in plastics. It is released mostly during manufacture or through disposal of materials which contain it. </text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
	<health_affects>
	<text>Exposure to high levels of hexabromobiphenyl can cause skin problems and affect the immune system and nervous system, the liver and kidneys. It may also cause cancer. Hexabromobiphenyl is highly persistent and bio-accumulates in the environment and may have long term effects on aquatic life.</text>
	</health_affects>
    <state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>72</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>489.9</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.00000000289</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>0.011</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>6.39</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>240.7</flash_point>
    <density>2.492</density>
    <toxicity>21500</toxicity>
    <persistence>Persistent</persistence>
    <aquatic_tox_lc50>LC50 - Colinus virginianus - 428 mg/kg 8 d</aquatic_tox_lc50>
    <description>Hexabromobiphenyl is a white solid, non-volatile and non-flammable.</description>
    <iso_provisions />
  </pollutant>
  <pollutant id="91">
    <pollutant_name>Benzo(g,h,i)perylene</pollutant_name>
    <main_uses>Benzo(g,h,i)perylene is used to make drugs, dyes, plastics, pesticides and explosives. PAHs are also created  when combustion is incomplete. </main_uses>
    <main_methods_of_release>
	<text>PAHs, including Benzo(g,h,i)perylene,  are released from combustion processes and cigarette smoke. They can also be released naturally from forest fires.</text>
	</main_methods_of_release>
    <health_affects>
	<text>Large exposures of PAHs may affect the eyes, liver, skin, and immune system. Some PAHs also may cause genetic damage and cancer. </text>
	<text>PAHs have an ability to travel long distances in the atmosphere when attached to soot particles. Therefore there could be adverse effects to wildlife in places far from the point of release.</text>
	</health_affects>
	<state>Solid</state>
    <melt_freeze_point>278</melt_freeze_point>
    <boiling_point>501</boiling_point>
    <vapour_pressure>0.00000000549</vapour_pressure>
    <water_solubility>Slightly soluble</water_solubility>
    <partition_coeff>6.63</partition_coeff>
    <flash_point>247.2</flash_point>
    <density>1.378</density>
    <carcinogenicity>3</carcinogenicity>
    <mutagenicity>Conflicting</mutagenicity>
    <persistence>Not Persistent</persistence>
    <description>Benzo(g,h,i)perylene is a colourless crystal-like solid that is one of a group of chemicals called  polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs).</description>
    <iso_provisions>
      <provision id="91">
        <standard>EN ISO 17993:2003</standard>
        <title>Determination of 15 polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAH) in water by HPLC with fluorescence detection after liquid-liquid extraction (ISO 17993:2002) </title>
        <target>Water quality</target>
        <uncertainty>The coefficient of variation of reproducibility ranges between about 2 and 5%</uncertainty>
      </provision>
    </iso_provisions>
  </pollutant>
</pollutants>